<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>How the members of the Church of England ought to behave themselves under a Roman Catholic king with reference to the test and penal laws in a letter to a friend / by a member of the same church.</title>
            <author>Member of the same church.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 196 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 114 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44620</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2961</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6451</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13505956</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13505956</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99791</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44620)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99791)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 791:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>How the members of the Church of England ought to behave themselves under a Roman Catholic king with reference to the test and penal laws in a letter to a friend / by a member of the same church.</title>
                  <author>Member of the same church.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 221 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by Randal Taylor ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James --  II, --  King of England, 1633-1701.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Relations --  Catholic Church.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Relations --  Church of England.</term>
               <term>Catholics --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  Legal status, laws, etc. --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99791:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99791:1"/>
            <p>HOW THE MEMBERS OF THE Church of <hi>ENGLAND</hi> Ought to behave themſelves under A ROMAN CATHOLIC KING, With reference to the <hi>TEST</hi> and <hi>PENAL LAWS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a Letter to a Friend by a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the ſame Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, and are to be ſold by <hi>Randal Taylor,</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall.</hi> 1687.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:99791:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99791:2"/>
            <head>THE TITLES OF THE SECTIONS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>SECT. I.</hi> THe Character of an old Loyaliſt of the Church of <hi>England. Page 1.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>SECT. II.</hi> How ſuch behaved themſelves, during the Tranſaction of the Bill of Seclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion <hi>Page 4.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>SECT. III.</hi> How the Biſhops and Clergy behaved themſelves in thoſe times. <hi>Page 14.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>SECT. IV.</hi> The Calumnies againſt the Loyal Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church of <hi>England</hi> in the foregoing times. <hi>Page 18.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:99791:3"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>SECT. V.</hi> The Affrightments and Arts now uſed to make Subjects believe that the Proteſtant Religion is to be extirpated here. <hi>Page 22.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>SECT. VI.</hi> That the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath been in a diſturbed condition under Proteſtant Princes. <hi>Page 27.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>SECT. VII.</hi> That it is in a more flouriſhing conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on now. <hi>Page 33.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>SECT. VIII.</hi> The ſelf-denial of the King in the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of his own Religion. <hi>Page 36.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>SECT. IX.</hi> The difficulty of effecting a change of Religion. <hi>Page 40.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>SECT. X.</hi> Two Objections anſwered. <hi>Page 56.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:99791:3"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>SECT. XI.</hi> That the Kings diſpenſing with the Teſt is no Argument of his deſign to Extirpate the Proteſtant Religion. <hi>Page 62.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>SECT. XII.</hi> That it is not the Kings Intereſt to extirpate the Proteſtant Religion. <hi>Page 72.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>SECT. XIII.</hi> Concerning the Teſt. <hi>Page 78.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>SECT. XIV.</hi> Concerning Sanguinary and Penal Laws againſt Roman Catholics. <hi>Page 143.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>SECT. XV.</hi> The Inconveniencies that will attend the not Repealing of Penal Laws, and particularly the Teſt. <hi>Page 165.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:99791:4"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>SECT. XVI.</hi> The Practicableneſs of Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lics and Proteſtants, living under one Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Government. <hi>Page 180.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>SECT. XVII.</hi> The Character of his Majeſty. <hi>Page 191.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>SECT. XVIII.</hi> The Concluſion. <hi>Page 205.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 15. Line 7. <hi>for</hi> aſſured <hi>read</hi> afraid. P. 22. the laſt line but one, <hi>for</hi> Theſe <hi>r.</hi> There. P. 31. l. 17. <hi>for</hi> confirmed too <hi>r.</hi> conformed to. P. 40. The Title of the Section ſhould have ended at the word Religion, and the reſt be placed in the Margent. P. 79. l. <hi>ult for</hi> it <hi>r.</hi> them. P. 94. l. 7. <hi>for</hi> naturally <hi>r.</hi> natural. P. 113. l. 12. <hi>for</hi> But <hi>r.</hi> yet. P. 117. l. 1. after <hi>we,</hi> put in <hi>may.</hi> P. 178. l. 7. <hi>for</hi> preached <hi>r.</hi> practiſed. P. 182. l. 3. <hi>for</hi> attemps <hi>r.</hi> attempts. P. 183. l. 11. <hi>for</hi> Budifir <hi>r.</hi> Budifin. P. 185. l. 7. <hi>for</hi> Abby <hi>r.</hi> Abbot.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:99791:4"/>
            <head>HOW THE MEMBERS OF THE Church of <hi>England</hi> Ought to behave themſelves under A ROMAN CATHOLICK KING: In a Letter to a Friend.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. I. <hi>The Character of an old Loyaliſt of the Church of</hi> England.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>INCE our firſt acquaintance, we have ſeen the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution of almoſt fifty years: In all which time your unſhaken Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, and ſteady Adherence to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:99791:5"/>the Doctrine and Diſcipline of the Church of <hi>England</hi> have been moſt conſpicuous. You equally hated the Flatterer, who by ſtretching the Length of the Scepter, made it unweildy; and the Factious, who by conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual filing, made it too ſlender, and of no more force than a Reed; or ſo ſhortned it, that from a Sovereign Battoon, it ſcarce equalled a Serjeants Mace.</p>
               <p>You valued him moſt, who paid a juſt Deference to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Prerogative, and was infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thankful for all the gracious Enfranchiſements of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. You knew too well the Injuſtice, and Illegality of ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Arms againſt King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, &amp; ſetled your Judgment ſo firmly then, that none of the Deſigners Arts, to cajole the Multitude, made any impreſſion on you. And however great your Sufferings were then, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:99791:5"/>by your Diſability to aid the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed Prince: yet you were as forward as any to aſſiſt him in all things ſerviceable to his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, not only in confirming your Neighbours and Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in their Allegiance (when their Enemies ſucceſs made them diſpond) but in making Converts of thoſe who had been deluded by the ſpecious pretence of Liberty and Reformation. So that you helped much to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare Mens minds earneſtly to wiſh, and effectually to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote, the late Merciful King's Reſtauration, and when in his later time he was ſo Embar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſſed with ſome of his Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: you were an eminent Abhorrer, and as ſtrenuous an Oppoſer of the Bill of Secluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and though you were brand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the name of Papiſt in Maſquerade, and a Janizary for Arbitrary Power, yet you kept your Poſt, and aſſured thoſe that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:99791:6"/>converſed with you, that Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty (which you had been taught in the Church of <hi>England</hi>) was ſo firm a Baſis to you, that the attacks of Slander, and Oblo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quy, ſhould never remove you one hair's breadth from your Duty. It was the very Polar Star, to which you directed all your Actions without trepida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the <hi>Axis</hi> on which you deſigned to move.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECT. II. <hi>How ſuch behaved themſelves during the Tranſaction of the Bill of Secluſion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>GIVE me leave to remind you of ſome of thoſe An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers you uſed to make to thoſe Speeches were ſent you from one of the Clerks of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:99791:6"/>Houſe, when the debate was hotteſt about the Bill of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion: for it was at that criti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Time, the trueſt Sons of the Engliſh Church, were diſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated from the Latitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narian Proteſtants, Non-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts and Common-wealth's Men.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>S. W. J.</hi> Collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Speeches.</note>When that overgrown Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer ſaid,
<hi>He took it for granted, that it was impoſſible that a Papiſt ſhould come to the Poſſeſſion and quiet enjoyment of the Crown, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out wading through a Sea of Blood; and without occaſioning ſuch a War, as for ought he knew, might ſhake the Monarchical Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> You then reply'd, This was more like the Bellowing of a Bull, than a Reſponce from an Oracle of the Laws, and that who ever lived to ſee the Duke Succeed, (as in courſe of Nature it was likely) would find the True Sons of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> ſo far from liſting up an
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:99791:7"/>hand againſt him, that if his Right were oppoſed, they would with as much Zeal and Concern as any, fight under his Royal Standard; and if any ſuch Bou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſeu's as he, raiſed a Rebellion; they would only afford Trophies to his Victorious Sword, and fall as Sacrifices to the Juſtice of his Cauſe.</p>
               <p>When that bitter mans Speech was urged, <hi>That a Popiſh Head, on a Proteſtant Body, would be ſuch a Monſter in Nature, as would nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be fit to preſerve, or be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved: and it as naturally followed, as the Night did Day, that the Head would Change the Body, or the Body the Head</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You anſwered, That we ought to conſider the Royal Headſhip, abſtractedly from the Subject-Body, as we do the ſublimed Animal and vital Spirits from the groſs Blood, and the groſſer compoſition of the Body. The Sovereignty being as a Preſiding
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:99791:7"/>Coeleſtial Power, fitted to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern Members of various Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peraments and Conſtitutions; and that it was as eaſie to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive how a Popiſh King might benignly govern his Proteſtant Subjects, as it was for a Father to govern, with Paternal Care and Indulgence, his Children of different Humors and Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and that whatſoever Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, other Church-men might take to obey Princes, only ſo far as they were Nurſing Fathers to their Church; yet the Principles and Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England</hi> (contained in its Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies) obliged all the Subjects to be dutiful, bear Faith and Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to their Sovereign, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port his Crown and Dignity, though he were of a different Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and it taught abſolute, and unconditionate Obedience for Conſcience ſake.</p>
               <p>When ſome thought to touch you more cloſely in your Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:99791:8"/>
                  <note place="margin">Col. <hi>B.</hi>
                  </note>Concerns; as knowing you had ſome Church Lands, and ſhewed you the Colonels Speech,
who ſaid, <hi>He took it for granted, that we have nothing of our own, if Popery come in; not only the Church Lands, but all the Lands we have will be little enough for them, for they will never want an Holy, San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, Religious pretence to take them from us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this you anſwered, That the unpractitableneſs of reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Church Lands is apparent, in the poſſeſſion of thoſe in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> got into by Hoſtilities, and eſtabliſhed by Treaties; and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that in Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s days, when the Romiſh Government, and the Popes Supremacy was re-eſtabliſhed, and the individu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Parcels (diſſeiz'd from the Church) eaſily known, in the Reign of a Princeſs ſo zealous to remove the Guilt of Sacriledge, that ſhe actually reſtored what was in her Poſſeſſion, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:99791:8"/>to the Rebuilding of ſome Religious Houſes, ſeeing, you ſaid, that ſhe, thus earneſt upon the Work, and who had the Intereſt of the Pope, and the Zeal of a much vaſter number of Catholicks then are now, to aſſiſt her, was yet ſo far from being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to obtain an Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for that purpoſe; that the Pope himſelf by Bull confirmed them. Certainly if this then was unpracticable, (when Proteſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm was at ſo low an Ebb) what could be expected after almoſt 150 years quiet poſſeſſion? So that if there were no other obſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle but the inextricable confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, it would be impoſſible that any Court of Claims could ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt the Title of any Religious to them, by any colour of Law or Equity: and no Catholick Prince whatſoever, would diſquiet, and diſoblige the whole Body al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of his Subjects, (both Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks and Proteſtants,) for
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:99791:9"/>the advantage of three or four of his Engliſh Subjects in every Monaſtery: for if he ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call all the Religious of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects out of all the Foreign Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents, they would not ſupply them to a greater number.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">S. H. C.</note>When you read another Sple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netick Gentlemans Harangue,
<hi>That Miſery and Slavery were the Concomitants of Popery;</hi> And when in anſwer to a Gentleman that urged againſt the Bill, <hi>That it would lay the foundation of a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable Civil War:</hi> The aforeſaid zealous Knight reply'd, <hi>That the Barbarouſneſs exerciſed in Queen</hi> Mary<hi>'s Reign by Fire and Fagot, might be put in the Ballance with all the inconveniences that ever happened by any Excluſion-Act.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I remember you pitied the Contlemans ſhort Memory, or want of peruſing our Hiſtories, where he might have found in many of the Skirmiſhes (beſides the ſixteen pitch'd Battels,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:99791:9"/>fought betwixt the Houſes of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> upon the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpation of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth againſt <hi>Richard</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond) that more were ſlain in one day, and more Families ruined in one year, than in the whole Reign of Queen <hi>Mary:</hi> And however the matter ſhould fall out (as we had no ſhadow of Reaſon to ſuſpect) it were bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to die, as Sufferers (guilty of no other Crime than the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearing to our Religion) then to die by the Sword, Bullet, Ax or Halter for Rebellion.</p>
               <p>You farther ſaid, That we ought to conſider the difference betwixt a lawful Hereditary Prince, and an Uſuper: The one being obliged, by Intereſt ſo to govern, that he may have a peaceable and comfortable Reign, and have willing and wealthy Subjects: Whereas the other (having the eſtabliſhing his Uſurpation his ſole ſcope)
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:99791:10"/>enſlaves all he can, ſtudying only to aw all into Obedience by force, and ſtrong hand: But it would be otherwiſe in the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion here, where the Princeſſes his <hi>R. H.</hi> only Daughters, who, or their Iſſues, were in the courſe of Nature (if he had no Son) to ſucceed him were mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to Proteſtants; ſo that he would have as great regard to their peaceable Poſſeſſion, as his own: And let the Motives be what they could, he would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent himſelf with the Publick Exerciſe of his own Religion, and affording Liberty, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance and Protection to all Catholicks, and imploying ſome of them, and ſuſpending the execution of ſuch Laws as were heavy upon them: And if this were not oppoſed, you doubted not but his Reign would much increaſe the Wealth, Glory and Military Diſcipline of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:99791:10"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">How ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous now.</note>Yet after all this, ſince you have lived to ſee ſo much of the Prognoſticks verified; of late, you have expreſſed apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the danger of your Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; and the concern for that, hath made you hearken to the ſuggeſtions of ſome Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and others who really be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve all which the Secluſioniſts then (without crediting a Tittle of it) moſt artificially ſpread abroad.</p>
               <p>I think my ſelf therefore bound to offer you my Reaſon, why you ought not to fear this, and in the firſt place, think fit to remind you how the Clergy of <hi>England</hi> (that ſurely conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered conſequences) behaved themſelves then, and after ſhall anſwer the beſt Arguments I have met with to the contrary.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:99791:11"/>
               <head>SECT. III. <hi>How the Biſhops and Clergy behaved themſelves in thoſe times.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Deportment of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and the Loyal Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, may be beſt known by their adhearing to the Crown-ſide, and the endeavours that were uſed to render them leſs credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the People.</p>
               <p>It is very well known how ſtrenuouſly they oppoſed the Bill of Secluſion, both in the City and Country, and how few (if any) of the Biſhops in the Houſe of Peers countenanced that Bill, which occaſioned ſuch bitter and biting Speeches, or ſuch ſly inſinuating Girds againſt them, as if they were ready to enroll themſelves under the Banner of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:99791:11"/>the Proteſtant Intereſt, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than be deprived of the warming Beams of the Riſing Sun.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Sr. F. W.</note>Hence one of the Active Members ſaid, <hi>They might be aſſur'd of their Religion, if the Fathers of the Church joyn in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt the only means to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it; and he deſired the Church might not be ſcandaliz'd, for they did not diſinherit the Prince for his Religion; but to ſave their own.</hi> And further ſaid, <hi>That he thought it a kindneſs to the Church, above all other Acts whatſoever:</hi> And leſt in this, he might not be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood aright, he added, <hi>that he meant the Proteſtant Church:</hi> which ſhewed that theſe men conſidered the conformable Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy of <hi>England,</hi> as a different Body from the Proteſtants at large; And ſo the kindneſs of that Act would operate to them, though not to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Biſhops and Clergy of the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:99791:12"/>Church of <hi>England,</hi> who defired no ſuch indirect proceedings to ſecure them.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">W. H.</note>Another ſaid, <hi>He was unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to detract from the Merits of Church-men, for whom he had a great Veneration; yet he could not but obſerve however ſince the Presbite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Plot, they preached up the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Phanaticks to be more than of Papiſts, and that to diſinherit the Duke was againſt the Law of God: Which ſaid oppinions,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>If they ſhould be Imbibed by the People, what would the Aſſociating Bill ſignifie, or any other Law againſt Popery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">J. B.</note>Another ſaid, <hi>That People were come to know, that the Clergy may be good Divines, but not ſo good Politicians: And that the Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men might be in a poſſibility of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing advanced by Popery (if they ſubmitted) but the Laity, under a probability of looſing all notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all Submiſſion:</hi> And added, <hi>That he doubted not, but
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:99791:12"/>that many of the Beſhops and Clergy, would as ſoon die for the Proteſtant Religion, as any Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the Nation: but he was jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous there was ſome over-ruling Power, yet amongſt them, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing anſwerable to that of a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Succeſſor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Gentleman ſeemed kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der than the reſt, in that he charged them moſtly with want of foreſight and inadvertency, that ſome Leading Men of their Order, were decoying them to overlook their Intereſt. But ſurely in this they Acted like good Politicians, as well as Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, in that thereby they ſaved a great effuſion of Blood, which neceſſarily muſt have followed ſuch an unjuſt Bill: And I hope they will retain the ſame Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity and Wiſdom, with a good Conſcience, as to afford no oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to their Enemies to cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure their defect of Religion or Policy, or allay the King-Affection
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:99791:13"/>and Grace to them for that Service then done to him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>SECT. IV. <hi>The Calumnies againſt the Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Members of the Church of</hi> England <hi>in the foregoing times.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Think it not unfeaſonable here to refreſh your Memory with a Summary of the Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies laid upon the Loyal Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in the Reign of the two late Kings of Glorious Memory. In King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt's Reign, the People, being wrought up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to repine at ſome ways of levying Money, not uſual, and ſome Rules of Uniformity either diſuſed, or not ſo Univerſally practiſed before; choſe in moſt places ſuch Members of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:99791:13"/>as they thought, would be moſt ready to redreſs thoſe Grievances; who, no ſooner were met, but the Deſigners amongſt them, ſet the People upon petitioning againſt Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations. Then the Biſhops, and moſt of the dignified Clergy, were accuſed of an intention to bring in Popery, and to make ſome approaches to a Conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very where hideous Crys were heard, of the apprehenſions of the Inundation and Inflowing of Popery, when the thouſandth Man ſcarce knew what it was, or who were the Preſervers of the Banks which moſt power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully kept it out; and having got Power by thoſe Suggeſtions, and gained an Averſion in ſo many againſt them, before they had over powered the Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, voted down, and, in the effectualeſt way they could, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally overthrew the Engliſh
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:99791:14"/>Hierarchy: And all that aſſerted the Government then exerciſed in Church and State, were branded as Betrayers of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects Birthright, Priviledges and Liberties, and Favourers of Popery, and Arbitrary Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Which Epithets they never failed to interweave, and on whomſoever they faſtned ſuch of their Petars, they were ſure to have their Reputation blaſted, and all their ſubſequent Actions rendred odious to the Commonalty, who the ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of any Mortals are blear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy'd, and diſtorted with the ſuſpitious ſquint.</p>
               <p>In the late Kings time, all Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Men, who profeſt moſt ſtrict conformity to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and were not for the Bill of Secluſion or Comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, were ſtigmatiz'd with the names of Papiſts in Maſquerade.</p>
               <p>How efficacious theſe Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies were to Arm ſo great a
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:99791:14"/>part of the Subjects againſt the bleſſed Martyr of his People, and bring him to that tragical end, is too freſh in our Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to need a recital. And when we found the powerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of thoſe Fictions and Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary Goblins in both Kings Reigns, to endanger the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of the Monarchy and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy: Have we not rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to believe, that there are a great number of Republican Spirits yet at work, who ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily mingle themſelves with all Male-Contents, and diſſatisfied Parties; and by their ſly inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuations inflame every ſmall Scratch, and rancle it into a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomous Boil, by their peſtilent and contagious Breath? Thoſe are continually raking into the Aſhes of every of theſe by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſt Deſigns, keeping ſome Brands always in the Embers, ready upon every light occaſion to be blown into a Flame. Can
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:99791:15"/>we believe thoſe to be now at reſt and quiet, to have huſhed or mortified their eager Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence of advancing the Good Old Cauſe? No, no, let us not believe the Fox hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got his Shifts and Wiles, or the Crocodile his Tears, or the Aſp his venemous Bite: Let us fear the gilded Snake in the Graſs, yea, rather lurking in every Thicket, where repining, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murs, ſears, jealouſie or diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent can lodge.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>SECT. V. <hi>The Affrightments and Arts now uſed to make the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects believe that the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion is to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpated here.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THeſe are a ſet of Men, who by their whiſpering diſſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:99791:15"/>and ſuſpitions of the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the Proteſtant Religion, are but fitting their Mouths, and preparing their Lungs to blow the Bag-pipe of Sedition: And when they have allured the Crowd, will endeavour to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coy them into the ſame Deſigns with themſelves, and excite us to follow the Methods they uſed in our Fathers days. That new Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pan doth much reſemble the old Varniſh, only they have found out new Exotick, affrighting Figures: And whereas before the Emblem of <hi>Venient Romani</hi> was placed at ſo great a diſtance from the Sight, that it was but faintly delineated, as in a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote Proſpect: Now they think they may be bold to place it in a nearer Light, and hope to allure the Tender-ſighted, and well Affected to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> to believe the reality of the Repreſentation: which is no other, but that the Roman
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:99791:16"/>Altars are to be placed where Communion Tables now ſtand. That the great Fabrick of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> is to have a Cupula with the Sword of that Saint, and the Keys of St. <hi>Peter</hi> upon it: That our Common Prayer is to he changed for a Maſs-Book: And in fine, that the Proteſtant Religion is deſigned to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpated.</p>
               <p>The Plauſible Inducements they pretend to have to believe this, are the Liberty the King grants to all his Catholic Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to Exerciſe their Religious Worſhip; the ſuſpending the execution of all the penal Laws againſt them, and the placing of Catholics, contrary to the Proviſion made by Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament to exclude them.</p>
               <p>Theſe Proceedings of the King, they would make us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, are manifeſt Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his intentions to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede from his Royal Promiſe of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:99791:16"/>protecting the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> and conſequently that it will crumble to nothing, by his withdrawing it.</p>
               <p>This they endeavour to infer, by the conſideration of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence the Pope and the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Fathers may have upon his Majeſty, who will be conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually inſtilling into his Royal Mind, how glorious an Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe it will be, rowſing his ſlow and unreſolved Thoughts, with the Conſideration, what a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual renown it ever will be to King <hi>Henry</hi> the VII. that he united the Houſes of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter:</hi> and how glorious the memory of King <hi>James</hi> the I. ever muſt be, who unit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Kingdoms: And how tranſcendent a Jubile it would cauſe over all the <hi>Roman</hi> World, That his Grandſon ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unite his Subjects to the Roman Catholick Church; which will be ſo irreſiſtable a Charm, they
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:99791:17"/>ſay, that it cannot be in his power to eſcape the Enchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Nor could he want the Charity to wiſh it, or neglect the eſſaying all means to effect it, being prepoſſeſſed with a firm Perſwaſion that the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking of it would be an accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Service to God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty.</p>
               <p>It is not my deſign to write any thing that may leſſen the eſteem and due regard Men have for the Church of <hi>England,</hi> of which I own my ſelf an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worty Member. Neither ſhall I meddle with any Points in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, but only offer my Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons why I cannot conceive, by the Proceedings of the King hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto, nor the conſequences flowing from thoſe ſteps he makes, That the Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is either in danger, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to be rooted out, or ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſed, as we are invited to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:99791:17"/>
               <head>SECT. VI. <hi>That the Church of</hi> England <hi>hath been in a diſturbed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition under Proteſtant Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BEfore I conſider the preſent State of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which I think, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reſpects, is as flouriſhing as it hath been ſince the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; I muſt ſhew its for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer condition.</p>
               <p>During the Reign of Q. <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> and the three ſucceeding Kings, it hath been continually diſquieted with Diſſenters, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naticks, and other Sects, who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver gave over their Clamours for a more refined Reformation from <hi>Rome:</hi> Every Year almoſt producing ſome bitter Inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:99791:18"/>or other; grudging, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring, and calumniating the Engliſh Hierarchy, to the great diſquiet of the Secular Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Hence the neceſſity of ſevere Laws againſt Non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts, ever and anon being made or reinforced.</p>
               <p>Thoſe that lived in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the late Wars cannot forget what Tumults were in ſome places about placing the Communion Table Altar-wiſe. How many were ſcandalized at the Biſhop's, dignifyed Clergy, and Prieſts Habit; at the kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the Sacrament, at the uſe of the Croſs in Baptiſm, about bowing to the Altar, and the Name of Jeſus: And tho' in Cathedrals a Solemn Order was obſerved; yet it was much murmured at, and was branded (both in the manner of the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebration of Divine Offices, and the uſe of the Choriſters and Organs) with the name of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:99791:18"/>down-right Popery and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition.</p>
               <p>Who hath a mind to know the particulars of the diſquiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> by her Proteſtant Adverſaries, may peruſe Biſhop <hi>Bancroft</hi>'s <hi>Dangerous Poſitions,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin's Hiſtory of Presbyterianiſm,</hi> Mr. <hi>Fowlis Hiſtory of the Plots, Conſpiracies,</hi> &amp;c. and ſuch as relate the Church Hiſtory of thoſe times; and they will find ſufficient to convince them, what Jars, Conflicts, Heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burnings, and Diſquiets were amongſt Proteſtants: How the Clergy and the Liturgy were deſpiſed; which grew every Year worſe and worſe, till it was judged requiſite by a ſtrict execution of the Laws to maſter the Nonconformiſts, and bend, or break them to a complyance, or ſilence. But the ſucceſs an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered not the deſign; for on the contrary, the peoples minds
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:99791:19"/>grew ſtrongly alienated from the Diſcipline of the Church, and as ſoon as they had choſen a Houſe of Commons to their mind, the uſe of the <hi>Common Prayer Book,</hi> Surplices, and Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits of the Clergy, and all things in uſe formerly, and eſtabliſhed by Law, were vot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed down; and the Souldiery and Rabble were encouraged to tear the Service-Book and Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices, to tranſplace the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion-Table, level the Steps, pull up Fonts, break down all the painted Glaſs-Windows, eſpecially where any repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Saviour, or any Saints, or Biſhops, or other in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Habits were: The Copes, Veſtments, and Chalices were all ſwept out of the Church by Order of Committies, or the Rapine of Pariſhioners, or Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; The Monuments and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numental Inſcriptions, were moſt of them defaced, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:99791:19"/>where a Religious Habit was repreſented, an <hi>Ora pro Animâ</hi> annexed, or the worth of the Braſs tempted the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; none of the zealous Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervers of the Rites and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the Church were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to enjoy any Benefice, or teach a School; Biſhops, and Deans, and Chapters Lands were ſold, and they were about reſolving which of the Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drals ſhould be demoliſhed. So that in concluſion there was no publick appearance of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> tho' all the Pulpits were ſupplyed with Preachers, who conformed to their new Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, and new Ordination by Presbyters. This might indeed be called a Proteſtant Church, but I am ſure it was very diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> as eſtabliſhed by Law, which was ſo far from then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a flouriſhing Church, that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:99791:20"/>it had neither <hi>Vola</hi> nor <hi>Veſtigium</hi> of one, but ſuch as was under as diſmal a Perſecution as a Church well could be.</p>
               <p>It is true, after the late King of immortal memory's Reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; It was reſtored again to a competency of Power, and Order. Yet the Diſſenters Meeting-places were as much frequented as the Churches. Everywhere Non-conformable Miniſters had their Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, till a new Act of Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity was made; yet the number of Diſſenters then were ſo many, that the King (who loved eaſe, and to have his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects minds compoſed, that he might more freely have the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of their Bodies and Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes) was willing to grant them Indulgence, till that was diſliked by the Parliament, and the Biſhops, and zealous Members of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> whereby the King was
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:99791:20"/>prevailed with to revoke it. Thus was the Church of <hi>England</hi> harraſſed under Proteſtant Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VII. <hi>That it is in a more flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing condition now.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>LET us now take a view of its preſent State, and make a juſt paralel, and we ſhall, I think, find it in no worſe, but in a better ſtate than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Now our Clergy-men go publickly in their decent Habits, are reverenced and reſpected, no affronts put upon them. All the Ceremonies appointed by the Canons, and Rubricks are more exactly obſerved, and more univerſally confirmed too, than in any Age before; we hear little of their Conventicles,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:99791:21"/>the greater number of former Diſſenters flocking to our Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, conforming in all things, anſwering to the Reſponſes, ſtanding up at the Creed, bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the Name of Jeſus, kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the Prayers, and with great attention and zeal, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the learned Sermons deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered almoſt from every Pulpit, the Miniſters redoubling their pains in emulation to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Fathers, that they may retain their Flocks firm to the Proteſtant Religion, and we may judge, by the crowding of the Churches, That for one Diſſenter that was won to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in the late Kings Reign, there are now ten, which is one of the Miracles the King has done, to unite theſe at ſo great odds formerly: So that to me it is a plain proof, that ſome people believe the Promiſe of protecting the Church of <hi>England:</hi> Which
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:99791:21"/>makes them ſhelter them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves under it; but I ſuppoſe it will be no longer than the Storm is impending. In fine (unleſs it be that we want his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties preſence at the Royal Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel) we find no alteration from what was in King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second's time, and the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the people, finding the Clergy ſo boldly to ſtand to the Proteſtant Religion, reſpect and reverence them more than ever.</p>
               <p>So that if the flouriſhing ſtate of a Church be to be known by the number of Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants, by the populous Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories, conformableneſs to the Eccleſiaſtical Doctrine, and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline: If by the decency of the Churches, the full, free, and ſolemn Exerciſe of the Rites of our Religion, by the eloquent, learned, and painful preaching of the Miniſters, by the full and free enjoyment of their Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:99791:22"/>the uninterrupted Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of the Eccleſiaſtical Laws and Diſcipline: The preſent ſtate of the Church of <hi>England</hi> is as flouriſhing as we can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, and may ſo continue, if we can be content to yield Roman Catholics a favour next to a Tolleration.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VIII. <hi>The Self-denial of the King, in the Exerciſe of his own Religion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SINCE I am diſcourſing of the paralel of the flouriſhing ſtate of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> formerly and now: I think we ought ſeriouſly to reflect how gracious our King is to us, and how little a ſhare of liberty to his Catholics, he is content with.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:99791:22"/>
               <p>None ſure could have count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it injuſtice, if our Sovereign had choſen his own Royal Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, in his own Palace, to have performed his Devotions in; whereas he quits that to the Prince and Princeſs, to the Archbiſhops, great Miniſters of State, the Nobility, Biſhops, and Proteſtants of all ranks; and contents himſelf with the Queens Chappel at St. <hi>James's,</hi> hath only one Biſhop, his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſarius, and a ſmall number of Chaplains, and circumſcribes his Proceſſions within the Cloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of that ſmall Convent: And at <hi>Windſor</hi> (his Summer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Palace) leaves the Collegiate Church to Proteſtants, and only keeps to himſelf the ſmall new Chappel adjoyning to St. <hi>Georges</hi> Hall, which if he had not taken (though ſome unquiet Spirits made ſuch a noiſe at it) he muſt have had no place there for his Devotion.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:99791:23"/>
               <p>The King graciouſly allows us the Cathedrals, Pariſh-Churches and Chappels, and the free and unreſtrained exerciſe of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; have we reaſon then to grudge him two or three ſmall Chappels, and the Subjects of his Faith, their Private Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories?</p>
               <p>We have had a further In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of his Majeſties tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in protecting the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in the Letter ſent to the two Arch-biſhops, at ſuch time when it was generally bruited abroad (we may judge by whoſe Artifice and Malice) that the King intended to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibite preaching of Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, betwixt the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> and us, and to take away Lectures, and Afternoon Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; whereas we find by the Inſtructions annexed to the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, That it was no more than had been done in King <hi>James's,</hi> and in King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt's
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:99791:23"/>time, and was verbatim what had been publiſhed by King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second: And in ſtead of reſtraining our Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters from preaching in defence of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> it is allowed, yea appointed them, ſo it be done according to the Inſtructions.</p>
               <p>Let us therefore receive theſe largeſſes of Princely Favours, with dutiful and thankful Hearts; and by no petulancy, or unneceſſary eagerneſs for more, indanger the loſs of what we enjoy. And I doubt not but Roman Catholics will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſomething to a people de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted to their Religion, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh betwixt thoſe that are, and ever will be, truly Loyal, even under Sufferings; and a party that ſeek all opportunities to repine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:99791:24"/>
               <head>SECT. IX. <hi>The difficulty of effecting a Change of Religion. Firſt, from the Peoples general Prejudice againſt it.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TO proceed more particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the further Reaſons, why I think the Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is in no ſuch danger, as ſome labour with all their Arts to make us believe. I ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire it may be conſidered, How averſe the body of the People are to it. Proteſtantiſm here has taken deep Root, and the prejudice againſt, and even ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrence of Popery, hath been inſtilled into us, with our firſt Rudiments: So that the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality may as well be prevailed upon to embrace Turciſm or
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:99791:24"/>Heatheniſm, as the Religion which hath been repreſented to them as Idolatrous, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Scripture. Education, and a long Series of contrary Uſage, are great Impediments in the minds of all Men, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of any change in Cuſtoms, much more in Religion.</p>
               <p>The great Obſtacle, that hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the common people from complying with the Roman Catholic Religion, are, That the Publick Service is celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in an Unknown Tongue, in which they know not how to joyn, as they do in our Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies, and the multitude of my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterious Ceremonies, do no leſs amaze them, who will be ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther contented, to be account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thick-skulls, than they will be at the pains to learn them.</p>
               <p>The Clergy, and thoſe who are able to conſider the matters in diſpute betwixt the two Churches, cannot (after that
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:99791:25"/>vaſt number of Books that have been writ on both ſides) ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie themſelves in the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation, Invoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Saints, worſhip of Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, Purgatory, Merit, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other matters, in which difference they unite with other Reformed Churches.</p>
               <p>And there is ſomething pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar, which will be a conſtant <hi>Remora,</hi> (to the Clergy eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially) <hi>viz.</hi> That, <hi>Firſt,</hi> the Reformation was here more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular than in any other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. <hi>Secondly,</hi> That Epiſcopal Government is maintained in good order; and ſuch a Liturgy and Ceremonies uſed, as come neareſt to the Primitive uſage, as they think themſelves very able to maintain. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> They are unwilling to yield the Roman Catholic Church to be the Judge of Controverſies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them. And as to the Supremacy of the Pope, The
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:99791:25"/>Engliſh Clergy will moſt unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly yield it, after ſo long a renouncing it. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> The In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpenſible Celebacy of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholic Clergy, is an inſupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable hinderance of Engliſh Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters ſubmiſſion to that Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; ſince the married here, will be incapable of preferment, and on the contrary, muſt ſuffer degradation and beggery.</p>
               <p>Who ſeriouſly conſiders thoſe things, will not only judge it an attempt unſeazable (eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally when the proſpect of a Proteſtant Succeſſor, is an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring-Office to our Religion) but may ſatisfie any of the groundleſneſs of thoſe Fears, (ſome people are too prone to ſuggeſt, more, I think, out of deſign, than that they believe it themſelves) That the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion is deſigned to be overthrown.</p>
               <p>There are but four ways, by which this can be effected. Ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:99791:26"/>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> by the freedom of preaching of the Fathers, <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,</hi> Their Writings: <hi>Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> Their Converſation: Or, <hi>Fourthly,</hi> by Force; which I ſhall now conſider.</p>
               <p>As to their Preaching,
<note n="1" place="margin">That it will not be effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the preaching of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</note> 
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> It is obſerveable, That it is a moſt rare thing, to hear any diſcourſe of Controverſies, in the King's, or either Queen's Chappels, or I think in that of the Popes Nuncio, or chappels of Embaſſadours: Thoſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants which have heard them, can univerſally teſtifie, That the Text, moſtly, is out of the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle or Goſpel of the day; and the ſcope of the Diſcourſe is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally incitements to the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Holy Living, diſſwaſives from all kind of ſin, and true motives to penitence for them. When they commemorate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Saint, in celebrating the Feſtival, the application is to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:99791:26"/>imitate their Sanctity, and praiſe God for the Grace con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred on them, and affording ſuch Examples of Devotion, and holy living: Which Heads, when they are moſt powerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly treated upon, may be effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual to make a Man a good Chriſtian, but avails not much to make him a Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic.</p>
               <p>It is well known to moſt that hear them, that if it were not for the habit, the <hi>Ave Maria,</hi> the want of Notes, the deviſion of the Diſcourſe, and ſome ſmall difference in the way of delivery, they could not diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh their Sermons from thoſe in Proteſtant Churches: So that they gain only by that, a little mitigation of peoples Cenſures, who have had them repreſented either as ridiculous, or abſurd. Since therefore the Preachers of both Churches agree in the points of Moral Piety, and the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:99791:27"/>Fundamental Doctrines of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity: It may prevail with Lay Auditors, to judge thoſe are the neceſſary things know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; and that the skill in nice and ſubtil Controverſies, are nothing ſo needful to ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as the decrying and ſhun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Vice, and Debauchery.</p>
               <p>When therefore we conſider the advantage the Miniſters of the Church of <hi>England</hi> have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Fathers, we ſurely muſt yield, That they may much more eaſily keep their own Flock from ſtraying, than the other can win them over to the Romiſh Faith. For, <hi>Firſt,</hi> the Miniſters are infinitely more numerous, and ſettled in their ſeveral Pariſhes, as ſo many Shepherds to ſecure their charge <hi>Secondly,</hi> They have willing, and unprejudiced Auditors to hear them; whereas moſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants that go to hear the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, generally do it out of cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:99791:27"/>or to cenſure them. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The Miniſters of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> have a good Art of Addreſs, to enforce their Doctrines; and having been longer uſed to preaching than the Fathers, and uſing a different method from them (to which people have been more accuſtomed:) I ſee no reaſon to fear that they can ſo prevail, as to commit a rape upon their Auditors Affections and Judgments, whereby they ſhould be converted by thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, as thoſe were at S. <hi>Peters</hi> Sermons; and without ſuch Miracles, I think, by preaching, the Proteſtants will not be changed.</p>
               <p>As to their Writings;
<note n="2" place="margin">Nor by their Writings.</note> the ſcope of thoſe ſeem to be prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, to explain thoſe Articles of Faith (wherein Proteſtants moſt differ from them) in ſuch a manner as may conciliate a better underſtanding between
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:99791:28"/>the two Churches, and by a ſweetening, and favourable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation of the Catholic Doctrine, endeavour to remove the Prejudices Proteſtants have entertained againſt it, as irro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concileable to Scripture and the expoſition of the Primitive Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
               <p>This ſeems the moſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an and Charitable method they have, or poſſibly can take, to render their Religion intellig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ible to us, or at leaſt incline us to leſs cenſoriouſneſs of theirs: which province the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux,</hi> hath undertaken with greateſt applauſe, and it hath been followed by ſome of our Country.</p>
               <p>Yet when we conſider how little hither to hath been gained by this expedient, we need nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the be waſpiſh and angry, or abandon our ſelves to ſuch ſink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſears, as if the Church of <hi>England</hi> would be overſet
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:99791:28"/>by ſo ſmooth a Sea.</p>
               <p>The Church of <hi>England</hi> hath in it many learned and dextrous men, who have good Libraries, and are well skilled in Hiſtory, and the Antient Fathers, and are well pleaſed, they have the opportunity of ſhewing their Talents, and are confident they can manage their cauſe more advantagiouſly than the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholics, and think this way of their Adverſaries Writings, effects not what is aimed at, but on the contrary, confirms the people, That they have been taught by their Paſtors, the more antient and true Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, as it was believed in the Ages neareſt the Apoſtles times: So when the Pope yielded to the <hi>Bohemians</hi> the uſe of the Wine in the Sacrament: It being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by them, as a confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, That the Euchariſt ought to be adminiſtred in both ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies; and that it was as reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:99791:29"/>that other Points in diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence ſhould be allowed them, the Pope recalled the Tollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>When we further conſider, That the dubious expreſſions of the Fathers, afford ſubtil men on both ſides ſufficient matter for arguing, <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con,</hi> and that the Writers in both Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, agree not upon a Judg betwixt them: It is not eaſie to conceive, how by this way, a National Converſion can be effected. For though the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Writers were never ſo much multiplied: Yet ſince the Arguments are the ſame, and neither part can put the principal differences to Umpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, or fix upon an Umpire, they may both write till Doomſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day,
<note n="3" place="margin">Nor by their free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to proſelite the people</note> ere they accord.</p>
               <p>As to Converſation, It muſt be owned that in this, as well as the foregoing particulars,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:99791:29"/>the R. Catholick Church-Men, have that advantage now, that they never had ſince the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, both publickly to preach, and publiſh their Books of Controverſie, and be as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious as they pleaſe, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with people in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, which is like a ſingle combate betwixt a Man skilled at his Weapon, and a Novice. It muſt be granted alſo, That ſeveral perſons may be recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> eſpecially ſuch as are curious af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Novelties, and not well grounded in the Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, or ſuch as fall into ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous thoughts about the ſtate of their Salvation, and come to think the failures they have committed, have been occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by their want of due In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: Or once conceive that Salvation is not to be had out of the moſt Catholic Church, or that a perfect abſolution up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:99791:30"/>Confeſſion, and Contrition is to be had no where, out of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſome may be won by an affectation of the modiſhneſs of being of the Religion of their Prince, or in hopes of the more propitious royal Smiles: and ſuch in my judgment, as change their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion for this ſole end, neither deſerve the countenance of their Prince, nor of any worthy Man; for ſuch will vary with the next Wind, and neither God nor Man will find ſtability in them.</p>
               <p>But we experimentally find that the progreſs of theſe kinds of converſion is very ſlow, and it muſt be a work of many Ages, to effect any great matter this way, where ſo thick-ſet preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices, and prepoſſeſſions of a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent perſwaſion, are ſo firmly retained, that to change a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion this way, is but like the demoliſhing a Fabrick of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſe
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:99791:30"/>firmneſs and ſize, by pick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out here and there a ſingle Stone, even while others are as diligent and induſtrious to ſecure it.</p>
               <p>If, laſtly, any be won over to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> by any of theſe, or any other method of more force, the act being perſonal, (ſeeing every Mans Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation toucheth himſelf moſt) why ſhould any ſo much be concerned about it, ſeeing it is their own voluntary act, and no injury is done to the willing yielder, and it would be a ſtrange obſtinacy in any not to yield to conviction.</p>
               <p>Having ſhewn the groundleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of thoſe peoples fears that dread the overthrow of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> by any of the three forementioned ways: I come now to the laſt, that is, Force.</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:99791:31"/>
               <p>It was a Maſter-piece in the Secluſioniſts,
<note n="4" place="margin">That it is morally impoſſible to effect it by force.</note> to repreſent Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery and Slavery as Twin-Monſters, and inſeparable Fiends; which they deſcribed in the moſt terrible ſhape, with Jaws of Lions, Talons of Vultures and Harpyes, Eyes of Baſilisks, and fierceneſs of Tygers, ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounding them with Fire and Brimſtone, horrible Flame, and the equipage of Chains, Racks, and Wheels, and all the Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Ten Perſecutions, or what ever elſe, inventive Miſchief hath ſince found out: Yet we now live to ſee them all but terrible Bugbears, and the Affrightments of Hypocondriac Dreams.</p>
               <p>By a natural inſtinct, we <hi>Engliſh,</hi> of what perſwaſion ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, are very careful to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve our properties, which in all times have been dear to us; and thoſe moſt antient Laws
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:99791:31"/>that ſecure them, were made before the name of Proteſtant was known in the World. We muſt alſo conſider, that with what ever daring courage, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious zeal may inſpire Men; yet common policy and intereſt, will certainly diſcourage all Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholics from attempting any change of Religion by force and enſlaving; leſt they or their poſterity, in the next Age might undergo a Retaliation as heavy upon them, when it would be more eaſie to extirpate the whole Roman Religion here, than now it would be to change that of one City. When there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the founding of Religion will be the ruine of Eſtates, and the Story of <hi>Perrillus</hi>'s Bull, is not worn out of Mens Memories, or Men are like to be the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices upon the Altars, they too precipitately raiſe; we are not to expect ſuch venterous He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roes, as will have the hardineſs
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:99791:32"/>of <hi>Sampſon,</hi> eſpecially ſince if they had, they would want the Power, and force to ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>SECT. X. <hi>Two Objections anſwered.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Know it is urged, That we had a ſad Experiment of the change made by a ſtanding Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my here, which was able to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow the Monarchy: And the French Kings late proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings againſt the Hugonots prove, That by force great alterations (otherwiſe looked upon, as next to impoſſible) may be ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected.</p>
               <p>But the Caſes are very diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from ours,
<note n="1" place="margin">That the caſe of the Uſurpers, over throwing the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy and epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy is very different from ours.</note> for in our late Civil Wars, the people were on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wrought up to the height of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:99791:32"/>power, to diſpoſe of the fate of Monarchy, by the belief the Deſigners impreſſed upon them, That Popery and arbitrary Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment were making great approaches, and fully deſigned to be introduced by the King and Biſhops: And a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was, by a fatal overſight, perpetuated, which was of the ſame perſwaſion; and had the Hearts, Purſes, and Heads of infinite multitudes to aſſiſt them in the work of Reformation in the Church, and redreſſing of Grievances (as they were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led) in the State: Which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch ſpecious pretenſions, and having a Parliament to pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronize it; and the Scotch Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to abett them, it was the leſs to be wondred at, that ſuch a Revolution was made, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when we conſider the Churches alteration was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo great, as it would be betwixt the exchange of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:99791:33"/>Epiſcopacy, for R. Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic Hierarchy, and the Popes Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy, which is here ſo much antiquated.</p>
               <p>Then the Doctrine of the Church was little altered, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept in that they rejected the Order of Biſhops: for the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice being in the known Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, without any Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, only conſiſting of Prayers, reading of Scriptures, Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Adminiſtring the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, according to the uſe of <hi>Scotland, Geneva, Holland,</hi> and the Hugonots of <hi>France,</hi> the tranſition was more eaſie, after the Army was victorious: Yet we have ſeen how ſhort liv'd, even that Uſurpation was.</p>
               <p>In our preſent caſe, a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is to be brought in, againſt the moſt earneſt endeavours, the firmeſt perſwaſions, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions, and the utmoſt dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation and abhorrence of the people: So that while we ſee
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:99791:33"/>only a mixture of Catholic Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, with a far greater num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Proteſtants, and a Body almoſt intire of Proteſtant Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers: We may as well have credited, That <hi>Oliver Cromwel</hi>'s Army could have pulled the Pope out of his Palace, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced Proteſtantiſm in all Catholic Countries, (as I have heard ſome of the Officers and Chaplains of that Army, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently enough hope) as that we can expect an extirpation of our Religion here, by ſo ſmall a number of R. Catholics as are in the Court, Camp, or Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try.</p>
               <p>As to the inſtance of the French Kings proceeding,
<note n="2" place="margin">That the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of the French King ought nor to affright us.</note> ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they that urge it, never give themſelves liberty to reflect up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the diſcrepancy of the caſe. In <hi>France,</hi> the King and the whole Body of his Kingdom are R. Catholics, and the Religion is
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:99791:34"/>eſtabliſhed by Law, and it is eaſie to obtain further Laws for the ſupport of it, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying of all others, by a King ſo victorious and reverenced; ſince how numerous ſoever Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants were there, yet compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratively to the Catholics, they were very inconſiderable. If in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the King of <hi>France</hi> were an Hugonot, and with the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of his Proteſtant Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, had been able to have brought all Catholics to his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, then there might have been ſome ground for ſuch an inſtance.</p>
               <p>If the advancers of this af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frightment would have been ſo candid, as to have ſubjoyned, how our gracious King hath granted, not only the French Exiles a ſafe retreat into his Kingdom, but hath likewiſe promiſed them a Protection in the exerciſe of Religion, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to the practice of the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:99791:34"/>Church of <hi>England;</hi> And to all ſuch hath granted his Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracious Letters Patents for the collecting the Charity of his Subjects for their Relief, (which is accordingly with a ſuperlative Liberality, afforded them) They would rather have made it as an Argument of the Kings inviola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble obſerving his Gracious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe in protecting the Church of <hi>England,</hi> than have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced it as an incitement to our fears of the contrary. But theſe kind of men know how to boil up Sugar to the bitterneſs of Aloes, and extract Poiſon out of Cordials.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:99791:35"/>
               <head>SECT. XI. <hi>That the King's diſpenſing with the Teſt is no Argument of his Deſign to extirpate the Proteſtant Religion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Know it is urged, that if his Majeſty did not deſign ſome alteration in Religion, what need is there of his ſo great ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitude, and earneſt endeavours for the taking away of the Teſt; and how comes it to paſs that the Law againſt it is diſpenſed with, and ſo many Catholics are Commiſſioned in the Army, and may be in other Offices? This being the continual Toll, by which ſome would make us believe the Proteſtant Religion was about giving up the Ghoſt: I think it moſt neceſſary to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large the more upon it, in ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:99791:35"/>how juſt it is in the King to imploy Catholics, and how much Reaſon he hath to diſpenſe with the Teſt; and that the refuſing the Aboliſhing of it, will be attended with much greater Inconveniences than the continuance of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">It is equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table that the King imploy Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lics.</note>Before I enter upon this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject more directly, I think it requiſite, in the firſt place, to ſhew the Equitableneſs, and Reaſonableneſs of the Kings imploying R. Catholics. In order to which,</p>
               <p>Firſt, we muſt conſider with what ſteadineſs and equanimity of Mind (peculiar to himſelf) our Illuſtrious King ſtemmed the Torrent of Antimonarchical, and Aſſociating Inſolence: and how undauntedly he weathered out the Storm raiſed againſt him, upon the account of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, before his acceſs to the Crown: So that we cannot
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:99791:36"/>think that he withdrew himſelf from the Communion of the Church of <hi>England</hi> for any Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Intereſt; and being not only ſo peaceably at firſt ſeated on his Throne, but by a Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous ſucceſs againſt a Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion (that was within a caſt of Victory) ſo firmly eſtabliſht in his Right: It cannot be thought but that he makes ſome reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on the juſtneſs of his Cauſe, and the favour of Heaven to his Religion; ſo that after we have ſeen him Triumph over the ſpightful and impotent Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deraces againſt him, and know him to be a Prince of thoſe rigid Principles of Honour and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, as in no time to make uſe of the coverture of diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation; we muſt conclude, that the World would judge him hypocritical in his Religion, if he ſhould not publickly practiſe it himſelf, and countenance the Profeſſion of it in his Catholic
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:99791:36"/>Subjects, and ſhew as favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able a regard to them, <hi>Caeteris paribus,</hi> as to Proteſtants.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi>
                  <note n="2" place="margin">That the King hath rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour his Catholic Subjects.</note> It is moſt natural for every perſon to cheriſh and confide in thoſe moſt, who are of the ſame Perſwaſion with themſelves in point of Religion, who are to be ſuppoſed, will moſt cordially and concernedly adhere to their Intereſt, as know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that their common Fortunes are interwoven. While there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Proteſtants, ſince the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, have been the ſole uſu-fructuaries of all the places of Honour and Profit in Church and State; and all, who have been bred Catholics, have been, ſince the begining almoſt of Queen <hi>Elizabeth's</hi> time, or at leaſt from the middle of it, under more or leſs continual preſſure: And a great many ſuffered moſt deeply for their Loyalty to King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt:
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:99791:37"/>And during the credence given to the late Plot, have been harraſſed from Seſſion to Seſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, proceeded againſt as Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, Impriſoned, and forced into Exile, or undergon the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere penalties of the Laws: It is but reaſonable that they, or their Poſterities ſhould, with ſome more than common emo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Joy and Contentment, entertain the liberty of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of their Religion, they have ſo long been reſtrained from. Nor is it to be wondred or repined at, that they are very deſirous to receive the Warmth and Sunſhine of a Kings Favour, they have ſo long been deprived of; and of diſcovering their Joy and Satisfaction, that they may be capacitated to render him Service, and be united in that dutiful Bond of Loyalty with Proteſtants, though they cannot accord with them in Matters of Religion.</p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:99791:37"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi>
                  <note n="3" place="margin">It is unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able the King ſhould be abridged of it,</note> It is a very unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Matter, that any So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign Prince ſhould be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridged of the liberty of placing his Favours at his pleaſure, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Compenſation of his Subjects Sufferings, or, as a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward for their ſerviceable Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty; or for the ſupport of ſome meritorious Perſon, or ſuch as by their Pen do him Joynt-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice with his Arms; the one awing, and the other arguing the Ill-diſpos'd Subjects into their Duty: And it no ways becomes Subjects to Murmur, much leſs to repine, upbraid, or offer at catechizing the Prince for it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi>
                  <note n="4" place="margin">It is an uſual practice among Princes.</note> It is a well known uſage amongſt all Princes to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain, in their Service, Great as well as Inferiour Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders that are uſeful to them, without having reſpect
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:99791:38"/>to their Religion: For the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty that any Great Prince gives to a brave Man, to Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe his Devotions in the way he has choſen, makes him ſo much the more at eaſe, to be ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous about nothing worldly, but the true ſerving his Prince; which made the late King not ill ſerved by ſome of his greateſt Sea Commanders and Captains, who had learnt their Experience under the Uſurpers, and were Non-Conformiſts to the Church of <hi>England.</hi> It is well known how long Marſhal <hi>Turene</hi> ſerved the French King before he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to the Boſom of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and how Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal <hi>Richilieu,</hi> and he, though they offered their Prayers at ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Altars; yet petitioned joyntly for ſucceſs to their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Maſter: And how long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the ſame King entertained Mounſieur <hi>Schomberg,</hi> and other Proteſtants. Surely the Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:99791:38"/>Emperour doth not reject the Service of the Lutheran Princes, and their Forces againſt the <hi>Otoman</hi> Empire; and it is well known, that Forreigners are imployed in the Councils or Armies of moſt Princes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi>
                  <note n="5" place="margin">It is but like imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of different Kingdome or Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries.</note> Neither can I ſee any greater difference in the Kings imploying of ſome Catholics together with Proteſtants, than there is in his making his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of both his Kingdoms, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipants with us Engliſh, in Offices and Miniſteries of State: Which to repine at, were very great Injuſtice, ſeeing it is what has been ever practiſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixthly,</hi> I may add further,
<note n="6" place="margin">It would be an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice not to do it.</note> that it were a great overſight in Politics, and an Injuſtice, if his Majeſty did not imploy Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lics; for it is moſt fit, in all his great and ſmall Services, he ſhould intermix thoſe he might
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:99791:39"/>moſt intirely confide in by the Unity of their Intereſt, by which a commendable emulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on would be betwixt them, who ſhould ſerve him beſt, or at leaſt his Wiſdom or Umpirage would be beſt known, by chuſing what Council to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, when they propoſed dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Mediums; and it would keep either party in that Golden Mediocrity, which is moſt uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to Princes.</p>
               <p>As to Injuſtice (which Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thet, whoever would faſten up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Prince, robs him of one of the nobleſt Flowers of his Crown) can it be other in a Prince not to beſtow Rewards, Honours and Offices (that are ſolely diſpenſable by himſelf) to his ſerviceable Subjects, or ſuch as have ſuffered for their adherence to him, or his Family, and perſevere in it? and none can deny but ſome Catholics are ſuch: And all Catholic
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:99791:39"/>Princes would judge our King a very unequal Diſtributer of his Favours, and to have no great Zeal for his Religion, if he ſhould not countenance and prefer ſome of his Catholic Subjects: Yet none of thoſe Acts of boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or choice he can do, if he cannot diſpenſe with penal Laws.</p>
               <p>Yet for all this gracious and juſt Favour to Catholics, I do not ſee, that by any the remoteſt conſequences, either the King doth deſign, or that it is his Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt by them to extirpate the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion, but rather to conciliate a better Union be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them, by converſation and mutual Service; that, in as much as in him lies, by the experience now, of that good Accord betwixt them, in the Civil and Military management of Affairs, a better underſtanding may be betwixt them, even un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Proteſtant Prince: Though
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:99791:40"/>it is to be doubted that, however now we grudge, that a few Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholics are in Commiſſion, and are peeviſh becauſe any are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed beſides Proteſtants; yet who ever lives to ſee a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Succeſſor, will not find the ſame reciprocal Favours to Catholics.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XII. <hi>That it is not the Kings Intereſt to extirpate the Proteſtant Religion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Reaſon that preſſeth me much to believe, that the King neither Deſigns, nor thinks it his Intereſt to introduce the Catholic Religion, ſo as to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude the Church of <hi>England,</hi> is the moral impoſſibility, that ſo wiſe and generous a Prince, and ſo great a lover of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:99791:40"/>(however his wiſhes may be, in his Judgment, thinking it conducib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e to the Salvation of their Souls) will undertake a Buſineſs that requires a long long Age to effect, and muſt render thoſe days he hath to live (which I wiſh many and many) full of diſquiet and anxie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, if not of Blood and Carnage. For it is a Princes paramont Intereſt to conſult the ſafety of his Government; and where he governs Subjects (as his are cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtantiated) ſo to manage Affairs, as he may not weaken his Kingdoms defence againſt his watchful Neighbours, by giving the Power into a few hands, againſt the hundred times more numerous, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly more able to ſerve him in his Defence, or give opportunity to ſuch (as we may be ſure, are not true to the Principles of the Church of <hi>England</hi> of non-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance) to raiſe ſome formida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:99791:41"/>diſturbance, which the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholics ſingly will not be able to quell.</p>
               <p>It is very evident, that the Doctrine profeſſed by the Church of <hi>England,</hi> is uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditioned Loyalty; and the Members of it, that underſtand beſt the Doctrine, and their Duty, think in this particular they carry the Prize from all other Church-Societies.</p>
               <p>But they are not all to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted Members of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> who go by that Name; there are ſome can be very loyal to a Proteſtant King, but can be factious, ſeditious Male-contents, and ſowers of jealouſies and fears under a Catholic; and think it no ſin to be regardleſs of his Honour or Succeſs. And if any Rebellion ſhould happen (which God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert) they would think it their Duty to ſit ſtill; and others who fight for pay only (of which it
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:99791:41"/>may be preſumed there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Common Sort) if up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any Revolt they had a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of Money, and the better ſecuring of the Religion they value, would ſwiftly run over to that ſide, where they might hope for both. Beſides which, the indefatigable Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths-men, Male-contents, Non-conformiſts, and ſeveral of the Zealous true Proteſtants Aſſociaters, and Excluſioniſts, would combine in oppoſition to barefac'd Popery; for they are all threaded on one String, the ſame Iron Sinue runing through them all; ſo that if by any Wars abroad, or Inteſtine Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents at home, any Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity ſhould happen, (which may fall out under the pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denteſt and wiſeſt Prince) It is to be ſuſpected by the mere ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Engine (the fear of loſing their Religion) the Body of the People would conſider their
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:99791:42"/>ſtrength only, and make their Loyalty give place to their great Concernment; and neither re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the Kings Sovereignty, or the Loyal Principles of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> but forget all Duty, and Reverence, to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure that which (they would make us believe) is dearer to them than their Lives and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes; and then the Catholics, and true Sons of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> would be only left to abide the ſhock of all the reſt.</p>
               <p>And though ſuch a Prince as ours, is not to be affrighted out of his Methods: yet we may rationally Judge that he conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders all this, and muſt compute what Hearts and Hands he is ſure of; and will not embarras and imbroil himſelf in Matters ſo difficult to accompliſh, and make his Reign uneaſie to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, by impoſing a Religion upon his Subjects, they are ſo much Strangers unto, and have
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:99791:42"/>ſuch an averſion from, and to no other end, but to force his people at the beſt to become Hypocrites.</p>
               <p>Having thus, I hope, cleared that Point, that the Proteſtant Religion is in no ſuch danger as timerous, or deſigning Perſons would have us believe: I come now to ſpeak more particularly to the Teſt, which is looked up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as the very Barrier, Rampire and Citadel, that is only left to defend us againſt the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powering Attacks of Popery; which ſome Men would make us believe, if it once be yeilded up to the Kings demoliſhing, no viſible hold is left to prevent the whole Nation's being ſubdued to the Catholic Religion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:99791:43"/>
               <head>SECT. XIII. <hi>Concerning the Teſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Shall firſt therefore endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to ſhew the Nature of the Teſt, and the occaſion of the making of it; and the ſeveral Reaſons why it may be prudence to revoke it, and other penal Laws. And laſtly, the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences of denying to repeal it, and ſo draw to a Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives that occaſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the making of the Teſt.</note>It muſt be owned,
that it hath been the Care of moſt Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Parliaments, eſpecially ſince the late Kings Reſtauration, to ſecure the Militia, and the Kings Guards, and ſtanding Forces in the hands of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants only: Therefore in the Act for Setling the Militia,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:99791:43"/>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1661, the taking of the Oaths of Allegiance and Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy were injoyned; and when it was known, that our King had left the Communion of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> the Houſes began to be more intent upon finding out ways to ſecure the Proteſtant Religion; and then thoſe, who afterwards, puſhed forward with ſuch violence the Bill of Secluſion, having gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo ſpecious opportunity, to lay all the ſtreſs of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivances, upon the neceſſary endeavours to ſecure the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion, under the noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of protecting the Perſon and Government of our late King, and preventing a Popiſh Succeſſor, from Arming Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lics to the hazard of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion; They prevailed upon the King to give his Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the Bills.</p>
               <p>I ſhall now give you a Breviate of it, in the words of the Act,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:99791:44"/>and give ſome ſhort Notes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and then proceed.</p>
               <div n="1" type="act">
                  <head>The Firſt Act.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Stat.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Car.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 2.</note>The Title of the Act is, <hi>For preventing dangers which may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen from popiſh Recuſants.</hi> And the preamble adds, <hi>For quieting the minds of his Majeſties good Subjects;</hi> It is enacted, <q rend="margQuotes">That all and every perſon or perſons, as well Peers, as Commoners, that ſhall bear any Office or Offices, Civil, or Military, or ſhall receive any Sallary, Fee, or Wages, by reaſon of any Patent, or Grant from his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, or ſhall have command, or place of Truſt, from and under his Majeſty, or from any of his Majeſties Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, or by His or Their Authority, or by Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity derived from Him or them, within the Realm. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or in his Majeſties Navy;
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:99791:44"/>I ſlands, <hi>&amp;c,</hi> or ſhall be of the Houſhold, or in the Service, or Imployment of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, or of his Royal Highneſs, the Duke of <hi>York, &amp;c.</hi> ſhall perſonally in the Court of Chancery, or Kings-Bench, take the ſeveral Oaths of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy and Allegiance, and receive the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, according to the uſage of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and the like for all Officers to be admitted to any Office for the future, within a time limitted. The Neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecters, or Refuſers to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged incapable of any other Office, or to Sue, uſe any Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Bill, Plaint, or Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Courts of Law, or proſecute any Suit in any Court of Equity, or to be a Guardian to any Child, or Executor, or Adminiſtrator of any Perſon, or be capable of any Legacy, or Deed of
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:99791:45"/>Giſt, or to have any Office, and ſhall forfeit 500 <abbr>
                           <hi>l.</hi>
                        </abbr>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>The perſons obliged to take the Oaths, ſhall at the ſame time make and ſubſcribe the Declaration following, under the ſame penalties, and forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as by the Act appointed.</p>
                  <p>The Declaration is in theſe words, <q rend="margQuotes">I <hi>A. B.</hi> do declare that I do believe, that there is not any Tranſubſtantiation in the Sacrament of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, or in the Elements of Bread and Wine, at, or after the Conſecration thereof, by any perſon whatſoever.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>There is a Proviſion that this Act ſhall not hurt or prejudice the Peerage of any Peer of this Realm, either in time of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament or otherwiſe: But this was in the next Act fully va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="act">
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:99791:45"/>
                  <head>The Second Act.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">30. <hi>Car.</hi> 2.</note>
                     <hi>The ſecond Act is Intiuled, An Act for the more effectual pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving the Kings Perſon and Government, by diſabling Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts from ſitting in either Houſe,</hi> and the Preamble adds, <q rend="margQuotes">That for as much as divers good Laws have been made, for preventing the increaſe and danger of Popery in this Kingdom, which have not had the deſired effect, by reaſon of the Liberty which of late ſome of the Recuſants have had and taken, to ſit and vote in Parliament: Therefore, it was Enacted, That no Peers of the Realm, and Members of the Houſe of Peers, ſhould Vote or make their Proxy in the Houſe of Peers, nor any ſit there, during any debate in the ſaid Houſe; Nor ſhould any Members of the Houſe of
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:99791:46"/>Commons Vote, or ſit there during any debate, after the Speaker was choſen; until they reſpectively take the Oaths of Allegiance and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy, and make, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe, and audibly repeat the Declaration following.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">I <hi>A. B.</hi> Do ſolemnly and ſincerely in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God, Profeſs, Teſtifie, and Declare, That I do believe that in the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, there is not any Tranſubſtantiation of the Body and Blood of Chriſt, at or after the Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof by any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whatſoever; and that the Invocation or Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> or any other Saint, and
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:99791:46"/>the Sacrifice of the Maſs, as they are now uſed in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> are Superſtitious and Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">Likewiſe no Peer of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland</hi> or <hi>Ireland</hi>—be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing twenty years old, nor any Convict Recuſant, that takes not the ſame Oaths, and make and ſubſcribes the Declaration, may adviſedly come into, or remain in the preſence of the King or Queens Majeſty, or come into the Court or Houſe, where They or any of Them reſide.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">Every Peer, or Member thus offending, ſhall be deemed and judged a Popiſh Recuſant, and ſuffer as ſuch, &amp; be diſabled to hold or execute any Office or place of Profit or Truſt, Civil or Military, in any of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Dominions, &amp;c and ſhall
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:99791:47"/>not Sit or Vote in either Houſe, or make a proxy in the houſe of Peers, or have any benefit of the Law, as in the foregoing Act, and ſhall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit 500 <abbr>
                           <hi>l.</hi>
                        </abbr>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">Alſo every ſworn Servant of the King, not having per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed all things in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Act required, ſhall do what this Act enjoyns, or ſhall be diſabled to hold any place as ſworn Servant to the King, and ſuffer all the Pains, and Penalties aforeſaid.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">The Proviſo's are, That Nine of the Queens Men-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, natural born-ſubjects of <hi>Portugal,</hi> and as many Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men-ſervants, ſuch as ſhall be nominated by the Queen, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der her Hand and Seal, are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt from the taking theſe Oaths, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <hi>Secondly,</hi> That none be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained from coming or reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the King or Queens
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:99791:47"/>preſence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that ſhall firſt obtain warrant ſo to do, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Hands and Seals of ſix, or more Privy Council<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors, by order from his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Privy Council, upon ſome urgent occaſion, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to be expreſſed; ſo that ſuch Licence exceed not the ſpace of ten days at one time, nor thirty days in one year, and ſuch Licence to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in the <hi>Petty-bag-Office. Laſtly,</hi> That nothing in this Act ſhall extend to his Royal High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>YORK.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Some Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flectione upon theſe Acts.</note>Whoever peruſeth theſe Acts (in the circumſtance we now are in) will eaſily, I think, yield, that whatever tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry uſes there could be former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of them, yet they could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be put in practice by a Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholick King, or that he could ſuffer the execution of them, as I ſhall more at large ſhew in the following Diſcourſe.</p>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:99791:48"/>
                  <p>In this place I ſhall only touch upon ſome few Heads. As,</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The Sere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</note>Firſt, Concerning the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in General, upon thoſe who could not renounce the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Tranſubſtantiation, Invocation or Adoration of Saints; theſe being purely Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphyſical Points of Religion, ſetled by Pecrees of Councils in the Roman Catholic Church; oblige thoſe of that Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to believe them, under the penalty of an Anathema; yet I think it is not eaſie to prove, that theſe Doctrines have any Natural Tendency to induce the Believers and Practiſers of them, either to endanger the Perſon of the King, or the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, which is declared to be the principal end why the Acts were made: and as to the increaſe of Popery, theſe very Doctrines are ſo far from working upon Proteſtants, that they are the very chief impediments, which
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:99791:48"/>hinder the people in General from embracing that Religion.</p>
                  <p>Therefore it muſt appear ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſevere, that all perſons, who by a ſpiritual obligation cannot renounce theſe Doctrines and Practices, ſhould be obnoxious to thoſe penalties, which, as convict Papiſts, they are liable to; and which, however vexatious and chargeable to them, redound moſtly to the profit of Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, Bayliffs, Clerks, and ſuch perſons as bear no proportion of Merit or Intereſt in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, to thoſe ſuffering Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholic Lords and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; and by ſuch Payments, Fines, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the Kings Revenue is very little encreaſed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons why made.</note>Although ſome may think, ſome of the branches were then neceſſary, to prevent all Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholics from enjoying publick employments, whereby the Managery of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment might ſolely be in the
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:99791:49"/>hands of Proteſtants; yet what neceſſity was there for the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawing of them, in putting them out of the protection of the King, and his Laws, or of recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving any benefit by them, ſo that they could not recover their juſt debts, defend themſelves from any injury done to their Perſons or Eſtates, nor have equity done them, which is the priviledge all Subjects claim from their Sovereigns Juſtice.</p>
                  <p>As they muſt ſuffer all hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips: ſo the Acts provide that no Proteſtant, or other, ſhould be beneficial to them, being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of all the uſual ways, whereby advantages accrue to any, either by the Living or the Dead, in that they might not be Guardians, Executors, Adminiſtrators, or receive any Legacy, or Deed of Gift.</p>
                  <p>Whoever conſiders theſe things with a ſedate and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed mind, undiſturbed with
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:99791:49"/>Bigotry, Suſpition, or Envy, muſt think this puniſhment in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to keep the Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholics in perpetual poverty and vaſſallage: which no Roman Catholic Prince can take plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to ſee, or endure.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Of the prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Rom. Cathol. to be in the Kings Court or Preſence.</note>As to the prohibiting all Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholics, or any other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuſers of the Oaths and Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, adviſedly to come into the Kings Preſence or Courts; there might be ſome colour for ſuch a prohibition, during the time that a Proteſtant Prince was thought to be in perſonal danger from Roman Catholics; but ſurely at any other time it appears a ſtrange ungentileneſs to retrench a Sovereigns atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, and ſhews a very unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming diffidence in the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of a Prince, and his Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy Council, as if they knew not whom, and when to prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit Acceſs to their Royal Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and Court; which by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:99791:50"/>to the Lord Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain, or by Proclamation might be done upon Emergencies. It looks like a ſuſpition, that the hinderance of the Acceſs of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholics was rather that they might not repreſent their ſufferings, explain their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on more favourably, make Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytes, or interceed for ſome ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed; which though not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in the Act fully, yet may well enough be interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the words, <hi>prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the increaſe of Popery.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I know there is a proviſion upon obtaining of licence; but that could extend to very few, who either could be at the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, or obtain the favour of an Order of Council for that purpoſe, and ſo all indigent Catholics, who for their ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings for Kings <hi>Charles</hi> the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr might merit the late merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Kings regard and benigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty were utterly, excluded.</p>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:99791:50"/>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Not fit now to continue.</note>But if we ſuppoſe theſe Acts as neceſſary and equitable, as the greateſt Sticklers for them could evince, while the Plot was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved; I think no perſon endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with common civility, will think it fit they ſhould be impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon our preſent Sovereign; nor will they think it equitable and juſt, that any Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic King ſhould deal in the ſame manner with his Proteſtant Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. And I preſume the Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Rule to do to others as we would be done by our ſelves, ſhould influence publick as well as private affairs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the King and Queens ſworn Servants.</note>As to the Kings ſworn Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, It muſt be very ſevere upon ſeveral of them, whoſe fortunes were bottomed upon it; and it was a very unbecom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reſtraint, that a Sovereign ſhould diſmiſs his Domeſticks, though never ſo experienced and faithful, for that, which, it may be few Members of the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:99791:51"/>Houſes would diſcard a Truſty Menial Servant for.</p>
                  <p>As to the Queens Servants, it had been contrary to the Law of Nations, to have impoſed ſuch Oaths and Declarations up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch as were naturaly born Subjects of <hi>Portugal;</hi> yet in that they were limited to ſo ſmall a number as nine (whereas her Majeſty entertains near thrice the number of Religious) it ſhewed but little conſideration of the number of Servants in the Family of ſo great a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs.</p>
                  <p>But I need not trouble you with the conſideration of theſe, as moving in a lower Sphere; for what ever will induce the two Houſes, to reinſtate the great Orbs in their places, and capacitate them to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ert their due Powers, will prevail to reſtore the <hi>Satellites</hi> of the great Luminaries.</p>
                  <p>Therefore I ſhall now paſs to
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:99791:51"/>the ejecting the Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic Lords out of their Houſe, and depriving them of their Birth-rights.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Catholic Lords, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded the Houſe.</note>By the Kings Royal Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative, the Power of Creating a Baron and Peer of the Realm, is only in the King, as the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Donor of all Honours, from whom all Dignities flow, as from a Fountain, to all his Subjects.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Conciliarii nati.</note>This Honour conſiſts not only in obtaining a ſwelling Title and Degree of precedencie, as ſpecial Marks to them and their Families of Princely Favours: but likewiſe hath, for many hundreds of years, had annexed to it a right of being a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Houſe of Peers, ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and voting there; and thence they are ſtiled frequently Hereditary Councellors, who conſtitute the Kings Supreme Court of Judicature.</p>
                  <p>In the Saxon times, and long
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:99791:52"/>after the Conqueſt, we find none but Biſhops, Abbots, Priors, and theſe (ſtiled <hi>Magnates</hi> or <hi>Proceres</hi>) to conſtitute the General Councils, which we now call Parliaments; tho it ſeems, by what we can col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect from the Ancienteſt Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, the King ſummoned which of theſe he pleaſed, and did not tye himſelf to continue it to their Poſterities.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi> 227.</note>But in the Great Charter of King <hi>John,</hi> we find he granted, that he would, by ſpecial Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, ſummon to theſe Great Councils, in Aſſeſſing all Aids and Scutage, the Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, Abbots, Earls, and great Barons of the Realm. <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cap.</hi> 2.12.19.37.38.</note> So in the Great Charter of <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the Third, thoſe are firſt provided for; and a ſevere Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication was wont to be pronounced, by all the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, in preſence of all the Lords and Commons, againſt
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:99791:52"/>the Infringers thereof: And it is obvious to all, who know any thing of our Laws, how Sacred an Eſteem the Great Charter hath had, being ſtiled, <hi>The Charter of the Subjects Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties,</hi> and looked upon as the Standard of the Subjects Priviledges; ſo that ſome are of opinion, that even Acts of Parliament, contrary to <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> are void.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Et ut Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rones tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctentur, te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neantur, &amp;. reputentur,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>&amp; eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum quili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet habeat, teneat, &amp; poſſideat ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem, locuus &amp; vocem in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentis, publicis Comitiis et conſillis noſtris, hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redum &amp; ſucceſſorum noſtrorum infra Regnum noſtrum Angliae inter alios Barones, &amp; Barones, Parliamentorum publicorum Comitiorum &amp; Conciliorum, Tit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>. Part.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 5.</note>This Right of Barons ſitting and voting in Parliament, is ſpecially provided for in their Patents of Creation, which may be ſeen at large in Mr. <hi>Selden:</hi> And, as to what relates to our purpoſe, is contained in theſe Words, after the Recital of the Words of Erecting and Creating them and their Heirs-males to the Name, State, Degree, Stile, Dignity, Title and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:99791:53"/>of a Baron, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That they ſhall be treated, held, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted ſuch, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and every one of them to have, hold, and poſſeſs, ſeat, place, and voice in our Parliaments, Publick Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions and Councils, and of thoſe of our Heirs and Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, within our Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> amongſt other Barons and Barons of our Parliaments, publick Conventions and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils.</p>
                  <p>This having been the long uſed form of the Patents grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by our Proteſtant Princes, it is not only an abatement of what the Sovereign intended for their well-deſerving Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and a violating of that peculiar Right, which was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to be tranſmitted to their Poſterities, and thereby a degrad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Roman Catholic Peers of ſo importent a priviledge; but it wreſts out of the Kings hands a Royal Prerogative he
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:99791:53"/>hath <hi>Jure Coronae,</hi> to make and create the Members of that moſt Honourable Houſe, which is his Supreme Court of Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. The ill Conſequences that may follow ſuch Retrench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, being well worth ſerious Reflections; and of the Kings Prerogative, I having occaſion hereafter to treat more largely, ſhall add no more here, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hint to you the Reſentments of ſome Parliaments, when they have wanted their Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and cloſe this Head with ſome ſhort Reflections (which with all due deference to better Judgments, and thoſe whom it may moſt immediatly concern) I ſhall only offer to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, p.</hi> 885.</note>
                     <hi>Anno</hi> 1255. The Earls and Barons abſolutely refuſed the King any aſſiſtance, or anſwer at all to what he demanded, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all the Barons were not at that time called accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:99791:54"/>to the Tenure of <hi>Magna Charta.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Stat.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.114.</note>So the Acts of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the 21th of <hi>Rich.</hi> 2. and all the proceedings therein were totally repealed and nulled by the firſt Parliament of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, becauſe the Lords, who adhered to the King, were ſummoned by him to the Parliament, and ſome of the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite party impriſoned, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peached, and unſummoned.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pryns</hi> plea for Lords <hi>Stat.</hi> 24.</note>When King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, ſitting the Parliament, confined but one Member, the Earl of <hi>Arundel,</hi> the whole Houſe of Lords Remonſtrated and peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned the King to take off the reſtraint, and to admit him to ſit, and ſerve the King and Common-wealth in the great Affairs of that Parliament.</p>
                  <p>So the Lord <hi>Digby,</hi> Earl of <hi>Briſtol</hi> being not ſummoned, the Lords ordered his Admiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to Sit, as his Birth-right;
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:99791:54"/>
                     <note place="margin">4 <hi>Juſtit. p.</hi> 2.</note>from which he might not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barred, for want of ſummons, which ought to have been ſent him <hi>ex debito Juſtitiae,</hi> as Sir <hi>Edward Coke</hi> affirms.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pryn ut ſupra, p.</hi> 145, 146.</note>When the ſame King <hi>Charles</hi> demanded the Five Members, the Two Houſes grew exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly diſquieted at it, and would meddle in no other Buſineſs, but adjourned themſelves to <hi>Guild-Hall, London,</hi> till the King ſhould give them ſatisfaction in diſcovering the Authors of that Counſel. The ſtreſs of whoſe Argument in their Meſſages to the King, <hi>Nov.</hi> 2. 1642 was, <hi>That by that means, under falſe pretences of Crimes, and Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſuch and ſo many Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of both, or either Houſe of Parliament, may be taken at any time, by any perſon to ſerve a turn, and to make a Major part of, whereby the freedom of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment would be deſtroyed, which,</hi> they ſay, <hi>dependeth in a great
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:99791:55"/>part on this priviledge, becauſe without it, the whole Body of Parliaments may be diſſolved, by depriving them of their Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers by degrees, ſome at one time, and others at another.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Plea for Lords, <hi>p.</hi> 414.</note>The ſame miſchiefs which they urged might happen to the Being and Conſtitution of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, by the Kings depriving the Houſe of five Members; may happen upon the Houſes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding their Members by Vote: againſt which Mr. <hi>Prynn</hi> makes ſo great an Out-cry, and from this unparallell'd preſident (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept in the long Parliament) of expelling Members for their opinion in Religion:
<note place="margin">Some Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections upon the whole.</note> All Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of the ſo excellently com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Conſtitution of the Two Houſes, may do well to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, what an Inlet it will make to the Imitation of the likely deſigning Men, when they ſhall have any Intrigue in hand to expel Members of other Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications.</p>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:99791:55"/>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cogniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Uſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>Surely we ought not to forget, how much it prolong'd our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable ſlavery, under the Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, when no Members (how duly ſoever choſen by the Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders) were admitted to ſit, unleſs they were ſo and ſo qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified, and made a Recogniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to own the Uſurped Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and to Act nothing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Model of it.</p>
                  <p>I think it no great Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation in us to be in Love with ſuch a Copy of the ſame, tho drawn in Oyl-Colours, and made more laſting and obliging by the Legality of it.</p>
                  <p>When Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> was in greateſt danger, from Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholics (even while her Rival lived) ſhe could not be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to deprive the Roman Catholic Lords of their places in Parliament.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The ill conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of Secluding the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops.</note>I think we ought to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber what diſmal effects follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Secluſion of the Biſhops
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:99791:56"/>out of the Houſe of Lords; and that upon the Kings Reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, none appeared more forward and zealous to have them brought into the Houſe of Lords again, than the Roman Catholic Peers did, which A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction none, I think, will inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret to have proceeded from their Love to their Religion, but ſolely to the tender regard they had to Juſtice, and the true Conſtitution of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and if the Biſhops and Proteſtant Lords, had thought fit to have been as careful of the Birth-rights of thoſe few Catholic Lords, that were Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of their Houſe, in all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability our Religion had been in as little danger by their ſtay, as it hath been better'd by their expulſion; for they neither were then, or are like to be ſo numerous in that Houſe, as to carry any Vote to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw or weaken the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:99791:56"/>of the Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">What ſort of Acts of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment leaſt dureable.</note>It muſt be owned that Acts of Parliament are to be looked upon as Laws the Subjects ought to yield all Obedience to: But it is likewiſe to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, that ſuch Temporary Acts, which upon Emergencies, and to ſerve a juncture, have altered any Ancient or Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Conſtitution of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, robbed the King of any uſeful Prerogative, or the Subjects of their Birth-rights; as likewiſe all ſuch as by Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of Time have the Cauſes, for which they were made, ceaſing: have been rarely found conducible to Publick Good, or of any long continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</p>
                  <p>It is true, our preſent Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign was perſonally excepted from the ſeverity of theſe Acts; but it is well known that ſome great Members of the Houſes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:99791:57"/>to have him preſented by the Grand-Jury as a Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, in order to his Convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as a Roman Catholic; and the Judges, for diſcharging the Jury too ſoon (as the deſigners alledged) whereby an Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment could not be brought in, were ſeverely cenſured by the Houſe of Commons.</p>
                  <p>This was not all; for the hot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Zealots were for proceeding upon the Statute againſt being Converted or Reconciled to the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> upon which they would have grounded an Indictment of Treaſon. And whoever conſiders all the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Excluſioniſts; will find they were bottom'd upon the ſevere Laws againſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts.</p>
                  <p>So that if his Royal Brother had been wrought upon to have conſented, it had been eaſie, by the force of the penal Laws againſt Roman Catholics, not
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:99791:57"/>only to have deprived our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign of his Right of Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, but of his life alſo.</p>
                  <p>Since therefore it is ſo evident, that the penal Laws againſt Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholics (as they now ſtand in force) are not only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to the Subjects proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but endanger as much the Rights of Hereditary Princes: In my Judgment the King hath ſufficient reaſon to require their repeal, and all Lovers of our Monarchy (reflecting upon the hazard his Majeſty was in, from them) have reaſon to uſe their utmoſt endeavours to have ſuch abrogated.</p>
                  <p>Surely we cannot but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect how things were puſhed on after the credit given to that perjur'd Man's Plot. How a traiterous party deſigned the late Kings Murther, the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of the Monarchy, or at leaſt the utter ſecluding of our Gracious Sovereign, and never
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:99791:58"/>reſted, till they had formed the Rebellion in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>So that when we conſider how theſe Laws were obtained, in a time when the Affrights, Heats and Ferments of the Nation were ſo great, and the drift of the Enemies to Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, and the Kings perſon, were not ſufficiently diſcovered; and when we conſider that thoſe ſo fair-blown Bloſſoms, ſo deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cately ſtriped, with the beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Colours of Religion, and Property, and Priviledges, were ſucceeded by the moſt poiſonous Fruits:</p>
                  <p>And that thoſe men who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended ſo much care of the Proteſtant Religion, manifeſtly deſigned the Eclipſing at leaſt, if not the overthrow of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> by their Bill of Comprehenſion; who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, I ſay, conſiders theſe things deliberately, cannot think the
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:99791:58"/>King hath any reaſon to be in Love with theſe Acts, which were made ſo Diametrically oppoſite to his Regality, and which would ſo manacle his hands, that he might have no power to beſtow Places or Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices upon his Catholic Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects.</p>
                  <p>Having premiſed theſe things in Groſs, I ſhall now proceed to give you ſome of the many reaſons, why I think the King hath juſt cauſe to inſiſt upon the Repeal of theſe Acts, and all other Sanguinary Laws.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Reaſons why the Teſt ought to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal'd. 1. That it chargeth the King and all Catholics with the deteſtable ſin of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry.</note>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi>
If there were no other reaſon why he ſhould earneſtly endeavour the aboliſhing of them, This one thing ſeems to me ſufficient, in that all his Subjects, who are capacitated to ſerve Him, muſt ſolemnly declare the King (or the Church he is in Communion with) Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, than which ſin I think
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:99791:59"/>no Chriſtian can be guilty of a greater, except that of the ſo inexplicable ſin againſt the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt. If I were a Military man, I ſhould be very diffident of ſucceſs, or that God would proſper my Arms, while I fought a Princes quarrel whom I judged an Idolater. And if I did not believe it (as their whole Church ſo ſolemnly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying any properly Divine Worſhip to be given by them to any but God, methinks ſhould hinder me) and yet were ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged ſo ſolemnly to declare it, I ſhould think I ſcandalized my Prince in the higheſt degree, mocked God, and gave a lye to my Conſcience: So that how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever uſeful it might be to deter perſons of the Roman Faith from taking it, and ſo to inca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitate them; yet I cannot ſee how a Catholic Prince can countenance or need it: And how either the King himſelf,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:99791:59"/>or his Catholic Subjects can di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt ſuch publick avowing them Idolaters, I leave to any ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal man to judge: And eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the King, being, I doubt not, throughly convinced in his own Conſcience, that he is no Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>later (for I think geſtures only, without ſome kind of intention of paying Divine Honour to ſomething that is not God, will not make a perſon guilty of that damnable ſin) It cannot but concern him in Conſcience to prevent, as much as in him lies, his Subjects averring ſo ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous an untruth (in his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties own belief at leaſt) and which aſſertion carries with it another ill conſequence, that every one is not aware of: For the Ordination of our Biſhops coming from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> if that be Idolatrous, it is no more a Church of Chriſt, but a Synagogue of Satan: And if it be no Damage, I am ſure
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:99791:60"/>it is no Credit to derive a ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion from it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi>
                     <note n="2" place="margin">That one great end of the Teſt now ceaſeth.</note> Another reaſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Teſt may be, that now there is no uſe of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect intendment of the Act; becauſe the end for which in great part it was made, is now obſolete, and totally ceaſeth: which I hope will be clear to them that conſider, that the power of the Militia, and the diſpoſing either directly or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>directly of all the places of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and Truſt, are in the King: So that though it was but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional, that thoſe perſons, to whom Proteſtant Kings com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted Arms and Offices, ſhould be aſſured of them in fidelity, (which the being of the ſame Religion induceth a Prince to confide more in) leſt their Perſons or Government might be in danger from any armed with power, that were Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lics:
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:99791:60"/>So that it was but conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taneous to the Sovereign Power, in diſpoſal of the Militia and Offices, that a Proteſtant Prince might refuſe to be ſerved by Catholics: and leſt any ſuch might get into Imployments, he might be willing to conſent to the moſt effectual diſcrimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating Teſt that could be invent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to debar them.</p>
                  <p>But now the King is ſecure from any apprehenſions of the leaſt danger to his Perſon and Government from Catholics, and can have no more doubt of the Allegiance of Catholics (without ſuch Oaths or Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations) than a Proteſtant Prince could have of his Proteſtant Subjects under the engagement of thoſe Oaths.</p>
                  <p>Here we may <hi>en paſſant</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve a conſiderable difference betwixt the method of our King, and thoſe of former times. Now we repine, and are greatly ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum'd,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:99791:61"/>as if all were loſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe here and there a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic Officer is Commiſſionated: whereas the King imploys treble the number (yea ſome ſay, Ten Officers that are Proteſtants, for one Catholic) and the Soldiers are generally Proteſtants; whereas before, not one Known Catholic was capable of any Imployment: We might have indeed ſome reaſon to murmur and repine, if the King ſhould commiſſionate none but Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lics, yet that would be but <hi>Lex Talionis,</hi> turning the Tables.</p>
                  <p>Therefore ſince he hath the power of diſpencing with that Law, as appears by the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence in the King's Bench, we have reaſon to be thankful to the King, for the diſtribution of his favours ſo liberally to Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, which hath been ſo long denied to Unfortunate Catholics; who, if their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on did not incapacitate them,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:99791:61"/>as Engliſhmen, Fellow-Subjects, and Gentlemen, are as fit for all ſorts of Imployment as Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants: And I doubt not but now that they are imployed, will as Bravely, Honourably, and Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpectly diſcover their abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and, I hope, will keep ſo good a correſpondence with Loyal Proteſtants, that are their Fellow-Servants to ſo great a Maſter, that the King may at leaſt have that ſatisfaction, that he can unite them in a Camp, which he cannot do in a Church; and ſhew his great wiſdom in Government, that he can be faithfully and effectually ſerved by all his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of different Religious Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts: And though the endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of ſeveral to explicate the Roman Catholic Religion more approachingly to the ſentiments of Proteſtants, have not as yet had that effect they wiſhed, yet it may be uſeful to let us ſee, that
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:99791:62"/>in affairs of State and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſuch an intercourſe and mixture may be, as former Ages have not known; and by the Conduct of our Gracious and Wiſe King, may be laid a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation for better accord in fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture times, that we may not be at ſuch feuds among our ſelves.</p>
                  <p>It is true, that under a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant King, there might be ſome reaſon to maintain the Proteſtant Church, ſo as it might neither be indangered by the Roman Catholics, or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Diſſenters, and by San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinary Laws (tho rarely put in uſe) people might be deterred from being of any other Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion; yet we cannot think that the ſame meaſures can be taken now, ſuch circumſtances varying the methods of proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and in Government and Politicks new Emergencies may, yea muſt, render old Axioms obſolete.</p>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:99791:62"/>
                  <p>Hence we take notice how imprudent theſe Informers are, who in our King's Reign, (more out of pretence and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent zeal, than for any good concern to the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>) tempt the Juſtices, and inſtigate them to proſecute Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholics, by binding them to Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and Aſſizes; for what can be expected from this, but it will exaſperate the King, and diſcover how deſirous theſe are to perſecute them, tho they know he will pardon the Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, in as much as it relates to himſelf.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi>
                     <note n="3" place="margin">It is againſt the Kings Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</note> Having thus far treated of the Natural and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Grounds the King hath to demand to have the Act re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed; I come now to the politic and more neceſſary part, as it relates to the legal conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the Government, which, by this Act of the Teſt,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:99791:63"/>ſuffers a great alteration in the abridging the King of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Prerogative of the Crown.</p>
                  <p>For the illuſtrating of which, I ſhall firſt give you the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the moſt Celebrated Writers of the Engliſh Laws, of what nature the Kings Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative in general is. Secondly, That the Leigance of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to his Sovereign, is judged among the principal Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of the King. Thirdly, How tender our Engliſh An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors have been of the Royal Prerogative. Fourthly, That the Teſt deprives the King of the Leigance, and of that Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Prerogative of having the ſervice of his Subjects. And, Laſtly, Conclude with ſome In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences from theſe Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Kings Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</note>As to the firſt,
<note n="a" place="margin">
                        <hi>L.</hi> 1. <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit.</hi> 90.</note> Sr. <hi>Edward Coke</hi> ſaith the Prerogative ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to all Power, Prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:99791:63"/>and Priviledge which the Law giveth to the Crown.
<note n="b" place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 1.</note> 
                     <hi>Bracton</hi> calls it in one place the Liberty, in another the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge of the King.
<note n="c" place="margin">
                        <hi>Fol.</hi> 47.</note> 
                     <hi>Bretton</hi> (following the
<note n="d" place="margin">
                        <hi>Weſton</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 50.</note> Statute) calls it <hi>Droyt le Roy,</hi> and the
<note n="e" place="margin">61.</note> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter ſtiles it the Kings Right, and the Royal Right of the Crown.</p>
                  <p>My Lord
<note n="f" place="margin">2 <hi>Inſtit.</hi> 84.</note> 
                     <hi>Coke</hi> ſaith, the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative of the King is given him by the Common Law, and is part of the Law of the Realm.
<note n="g" place="margin">
                        <hi>Prerog. c.</hi> 1.</note> 
                     <hi>Stanford</hi> ſaith the Prerogative hath its Being from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law, and the Statutes are but declarative. Properly ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the Prerogatives of the Crown are ſuch powers as the Kings of <hi>England</hi> have reſerved to themſelves, as moſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for the ſupport of their Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and the Government.</p>
                  <p>Therefore
<note n="h" place="margin">
                        <hi>Ruſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>w. Collect.</hi> 555.</note> Sr. <hi>John Banks</hi> in his argument about Ship-mony, affirms that the <hi>Jura Summae
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:99791:64"/>Majeſtatis, which are the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatives, are given to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the King by the Common Law, and the Supreme Dominion is inherent in his Perſon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Another judicious
<note n="i" place="margin">
                        <hi>Mr. White Majeſtas Intemera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta.</hi> p. 30.</note> Lawyer, out of the Authorities he there cites, ſaith, <hi>The Prerogative is inſeparable from his Perſon, not grantable over, it is always ſtuck upon the King or Crown, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inherent to the Majeſty of a King, and part of the matter of that Majeſty, is no more grantable, than the Majeſty it ſelf, or a Royal member of the Imperial Stile.</hi> Theſe are the Characters given to the Kings Prerogative in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. The Subjects <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> the Crown.</note>Let us now in the ſecond place conſider, that among the Prerogatives of the Crown, It hath been always accounted one of the eminenteſt, principal, and fundamental ones, that the King, and none but he, may at
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:99791:64"/>his own pleaſure command the ſervice of all, and every his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects in his Wars, and other Miniſterial Offices, which they are bound to, by their Natural Allegiance.</p>
                  <p>Hence
<note n="k" place="margin">2 <hi>Instit.</hi> 128.</note> Sr. <hi>Edward Coke</hi> ſtiles Leigeance the higheſt and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt obligation of Duty and Obedience that can be, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines it <hi>The true and faithful obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of a Liege man to his Liege Lord or Sovereign,</hi> and ſo calls it
<note n="*" place="margin">Vincu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum Fidei, &amp; Leges eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentia.</note> 
                     <hi>The Ligement or bond of Faith, and the eſſence of the Law,</hi> and in
<note n="l" place="margin">7 <hi>Rep. p.</hi> 9. <hi>amit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit Regnum ſed non Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem, amit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit Patriam ſed non Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trem Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie.</hi>
                     </note> another place he affirms, <hi>That it is not in the power of any Subject to diſſolve this Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation,</hi> ſaying, <hi>That he that abjures the Realm, may looſe the Kingdom, but not the King, may looſe his Country, but not the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of his Country;</hi> agreeable to what another eminent
<note n="m" place="margin">
                        <hi>Dyer. fol.</hi> 300.</note> Lawyer aſſerts, <hi>That none can diveſt himſelf of his Country, in which he is born, nor abjure his
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:99791:65"/>due Allegiance,</hi> nemo patriam qua natus eſt exuere, nec lige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anciam debitam ejurare poteſt.</p>
                  <p>In <hi>Calvin</hi>'s Caſe the famous
<note n="n" place="margin">7 <hi>Rep. p.</hi> 4.</note> Chief Juſtice ſaith, <hi>That Lie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance and Obedience is an Inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent inſeparable to every Subject: For as ſoon as he is born, he oweth by Birthright, Liegiance and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to his Sovereign,</hi> therefore in ſeveral Acts of
<note n="o" place="margin">14 H. 8.61. 43 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> Parliament, the King is called <hi>The liege and natural liege Lord of his Subjects,</hi> and his people, <hi>natural liege Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects.</hi> So that the liegiance is due to the natural perſon of the King, by the Law of Nature, which is immutable; is part of the Law of <hi>England;</hi> and was before judicial and municipal Laws, as the ſame great Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor affirms.</p>
                  <p>Long before him
<note n="p" place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Stanford Plea</hi> 54.</note> 
                     <hi>Bracton</hi> ſaith, <hi>That things which are an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to juſtice and peace, belong to none but the Crown, and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity Royal, nor can they be ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:99791:65"/>from the Crown, for they make the Crown.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is a known maxim in Law, ſaith the learned
<note n="q" place="margin">
                        <hi>Coke Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port</hi> 7, <hi>p.</hi> 7. <hi>ex Stat.</hi> 11. <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 1. 2 <hi>Eliz c.</hi> 2</note> Judge, that <hi>every Subject is bound to defend the King, and to go with the King, and to ſerve in his Wars, as well without, as within the Realm.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Liegeance to the Prince, ſaith a ſingularly well read
<note n="r" place="margin">Majeſtas Intemerata.</note> Lawyer, is immutable, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute, in all places: It obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth in all <hi>ubi's,</hi> and the liege man ought in duty of this faith, to perform to his Lord the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of a Subject, when ever he ſhall need his aſſiſtance, againſt all who <hi>mori poſſunt aut vive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,</hi> can die or live.</p>
                  <p>This is clear by Law and Reaſon. In the 48
<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                        <hi>Claus</hi> 48. <hi>H.</hi> 3. <hi>M.</hi> 3. <hi>Tam militi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e quam liberi homines &amp; omnes alii ad defenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem Regis tenentur.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>H.</hi> 3. the words of the Law are, <hi>That the Knights and Free-tenants, and all others were obliged to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the King:</hi> And ſo 12 <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>All and every ſingle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:99791:66"/>are bound to defend the King.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thence it was, that a
<note n="t" place="margin">4 <hi>Inſtit.</hi> 7. <hi>In <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>lo Heſtium ſuorum.</hi>
                     </note> Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment judged it High Treaſon in <hi>Nicholas Segrave,</hi> that he with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew himſelf from the Kings Hoſte, leaving the King in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of his Enemies.</p>
                  <p>The ground of all which is what
<note n="u" place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> 
                     <hi>Bracton</hi> ſo long ſince hath noted, that to receive Juſtice and Protection, are the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt benefits of this Life, and there can be no uſe of
<note n="w" place="margin">
                        <hi>Com.</hi> 3.5.</note> Rulers without theſe Attributes; for if the Sovereign be abridged
<note n="x" place="margin">
                        <hi>Roll. Eritt.</hi> 234.</note> of the Prerogative to exact Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and Liegiance from his Subjects, he hath but a ſmall portion of the Sovereignty; indeed his Kingſhip muſt be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carious, as depending only on the good Nature of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects.</p>
                  <p>Thence the Attorney
<note n="y" place="margin">
                        <hi>Puſw.</hi> Col cer. <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi> 552,</note> General in the Argument of Ship-money ſaith, <hi>The King (as Head of the
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:99791:66"/>Politic Body) is furniſhed with intire Power and Juriſdiction, not only to miniſter Juſtice in Cauſes Eccleſiaſtical and Temporal unto his People, but likewiſe for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence both of the one and of the other:</hi> Whence the Clauſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted in the Regiſter, <hi>Ad pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videndam Salvationem Regis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bracton</hi>
                     <note n="z" place="margin">2 <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>fol.</hi> 6.</note> ſaith, <hi>The Life and Members of every Subject are in the Power of the King:</hi> And a
<note n="a" place="margin">
                        <hi>Paſch.</hi> 19 <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>Rol.</hi> 36. <hi>North.</hi>
                     </note> Record ſaith, <hi>Vita &amp; membra ſunt in manu Regis;</hi> both which are underſtood, that the King hath ſole Power to command their Service in his Wars, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe as he hath occaſion.</p>
                  <p>The Lord Chief
<note n="b" place="margin">
                        <hi>Inſtit.</hi> 149. <hi>Weſt.</hi> 2.39. 1 <hi>R.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 15. <hi>Rol. Brit.</hi> 85.</note> Juſtice ſaith, <hi>That if any Privy Councellor, or other, cauſe one to enter into an obligation to ſerve the King, it is void; every man being bound to ſerve him without it, and ſuch Writings are declared diſhonour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; being every man is bound to defend the King and his Realm,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:99791:67"/>and to do the ſervice that apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth to him as his Liege Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The King
<note n="c" place="margin">
                        <hi>Com. pl.</hi> 316.</note> is ſtiled the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign and Chief Captain of Arms, all Power is his, no man may uſe Arms, ſo much as in Turnament, Tilt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> without the Kings Licenſe: The
<note n="d" place="margin">
                        <hi>Rol. Parl.</hi> 5 <hi>H.</hi> 4. <hi>N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
                        </hi> 24.</note> Statute of <hi>Array</hi> is full in this, tho' not printed.</p>
                  <p>This is further illuſtrated in that, if a Sheriff return that he is reſiſted in ſerving the Kings Writ; it is declared not to be good, becauſe it redounds to the Kings diſhonour, being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed the King can command every one to obey: and the Sheriff hath Authority from him to raiſe the <hi>Poſſe Commitatus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In former Ages, the Kings abſolute Power in diſpoſing the Militia, was never diſputed. It was the black or bloody Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament only, that aſſumed to themſelves coordinate Power,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:99791:67"/>and challenged the Power of ordering the Militia, for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving the Kingdom, without and againſt the Kings conſent; which occaſioned the firſt Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond to declare in the pream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the Act
<note n="e" place="margin">13 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 6. 14 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> 
                     <hi>That it is, and ever was the Kings Prerogative alone to diſpoſe of the Militia of the Nation, to make War and Peace, League and Truce, to grant ſafe Conduct without the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and that he may Iſſue out Commiſſions of Lieutenancy, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powering them to form into Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments, and imploy them as well within their own, as other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, as the King ſhall direct.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Since the taking away Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nures, it is true, the Method of raiſing Men hath been ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing altered; but before the impoſing of the Oaths of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy and Allegiance, and now this Teſt, we find no qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications of the perſons re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:99791:68"/>but that they ſhould be <hi>habiles Corporis,</hi> of able Bodies, ſit to ſerve the King and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try: And tho this Teſt doth not totally deprive the King of the ſervice of his Subjects; yet it diminiſheth his Authority, and takes away the corporal Service of a conſiderable num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of his Liege people.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Thirdly.</hi> Hew care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful our Anceſtors have been to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives.</note>I now paſs to the third parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, in which I ſhall in ſome few inſtances ſhew how careful the Houſes of Parliament have been in preſerving inviolable the Prerogative of the Crown; or when by any preſſing emer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency they have been invaded, that the Judges have deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined that the Kings of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> might by a ſpecial <hi>non ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtante</hi> diſpence with the penalty of them.</p>
                  <p>This Queſtion about the Teſt being wholly new, and ſuch a weakening of the Prerogative
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:99791:68"/>as hath not been known in our Anceſtors days, you cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect any clear diſciſſion of it in the Books of the Law. All one can do in ſuch a caſe, is only to produce ſome Maxims, Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, or parallel Caſes that may affect it moſt, which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the help of any ones Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections, as having never peruſed any of the Arguments in Sir <hi>Edward Hales</hi> Caſe, I ſhall out of my own ſmall reading offer theſe following to your conſideration.</p>
                  <p>The Attorney
<note n="f" place="margin">
                        <hi>Ruſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth</hi>'s Collect, 578.</note> General af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms, <hi>That an Act of Parliament doth not extend to take away the Common Right of the Crown,</hi> and ſaith, <hi>That hath been the expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Judges, of Acts of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament that have done ſo.</hi> He inſtanceth in the <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> of King <hi>Johns</hi> 17<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 
                     <hi>Regni,</hi> where it is ſaid, <hi>That no Scutage or Aid ſhould be without aſſent of Parliament:</hi> So that in this there
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:99791:69"/>was no exception of an Aid to Knight the Kings Eldeſt Son, or marry his Eldeſt Daughter; yet it was reſolved in this caſe, that by that Charter thoſe Aids were not aboliſhed, they being due by the Law of the Land, and ſo it was declared, 25 <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</p>
                  <p>We find an Antient Statute in King
<note n="g" place="margin">
                        <hi>Weſtonſ. c.</hi> 50. 2 <hi>Inſtit.</hi> 263.</note> 
                     <hi>Edward</hi> the Firſt's time, wherein the King ſpeaks thus, <hi>That he bad done this for the Honour of God, the Honour of the Church, for the Common-weal, and for the remedy, disburthening and eaſe of them that be grieved; yet this ſhould not be prejudicial to him, or to his Crown, but that the Right, which to him appertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, ſhould be ſaved:</hi> Which Sir <hi>Edward Coke</hi> calls the Kings Right of his Crown and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative.</p>
                  <p>It is declared by the Lords and Commons in full
<note n="h" place="margin">Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l. Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. 43 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</hi> 7.</note> Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, upon demand by the
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:99791:69"/>King, <hi>That they would not aſſent to any thing in Parliament that tended to the diſinhereſon of the King and the Crown, whereto they were ſworn.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This makes the Chief
<note n="i" place="margin">4 <hi>Iucti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi> 51.</note> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice cenſure as a great fault the omiſſion in the printed Statute of 2 <hi>R.</hi> 2. in confirmation of Liberties theſe Words, <hi>Saving to the King his Regality,</hi> which are found in the Parliament
<note n="k" place="margin">Roll. Parlam. 2 <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>Stat.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 4.</note> Roll.</p>
                  <p>A Lawyer
<note n="l" place="margin">
                        <hi>Davis</hi> Reports 86.</note> of no ſmall eſteem ſaith, <hi>The Commons of</hi> England <hi>have ever been exemplary for the tenderneſs of the Kings Honour, and the maintenance of the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reignty:</hi> But this was before they medled ſo much with Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of Religion.</p>
                  <p>So in latter times 3<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 
                     <hi>Car.</hi> 1. both Houſes declared, upon paſſing the Petition of Right, <hi>that they have neither intention nor power to hurt the Kings Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatives.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="132" facs="tcp:99791:70"/>
                  <p>Thus far as to the regard our Anceſtors have had to the Royal Prerogative. Now I ſhall in a few particulars ſhew the reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Judges, in ſuch Caſes, when Acts of Parliament have intrenched upon them.</p>
                  <p>In the 13th of
<note n="m" place="margin">4 <hi>Inſtitu.</hi> 42. How the Judges have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Acts of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that Inſringe the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regative.</note> 
                     <hi>Richard</hi> the Second. <hi>Stat.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. it was enacted, <hi>That no Charter of Pardon, unleſs ſo and ſo qualified, ſhould be from thenceforth allowed by the Juſtices for Murther, Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or Rape, and if it were other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, the Charter to be diſallowed:</hi> Yet my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> ſaith, <hi>This did not bind the King, the granting of Pardon being the Kings Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative, incident ſolely and inſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to the Perſon of the King.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſame <hi>Richard</hi> the Second bequeathed
<note n="n" place="margin">Ibid.</note> certain Treaſuries to his Succeſſor, on condition to obſerve the Acts made the 21 <hi>Reg. This was held unjuſt and unlawful, for that it reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Sovereign Liberty of the
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:99791:70"/>King his Succeſſor. And the ſame Reaſon,</hi> ſaith a judicious
<note n="o" place="margin">Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtas Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morata.</note> Lawyer, <hi>may ſerve to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw a Statute, which ſhall unjuſtly and unlawfully reſtrain the ſame Sovereign: Nor had,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>this bequeſt been of more ſtrength, had it been enacted by Parliament; Injuſtice being Injuſtice, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawfulneſs <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawfulneſs every where.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It was
<note n="p" place="margin">
                        <hi>Cokes</hi> Report. 12. <hi>p.</hi> 14.</note> enacted 23 <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>That no man ſhould ſerve the King as Sheriff in any County above one year, but the Grant ſhould be void, the perſon accepting it, pay two hundred pound; and it was expreſly provided, that the King by a</hi> non obſtante <hi>ſhould not diſpence with it.</hi> Yet it was agreed 2 <hi>H.</hi> 7. againſt the expreſs proviſion of that Act, <hi>That the King may, by a ſpecial</hi> non obſtante, <hi>diſpence with the Act, becauſe no Act could debar the King from the ſervice of his Subjects, which the Law of
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:99791:71"/>Nature did give unto him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the 37 <hi>H.</hi> 6. it was
<note n="q" place="margin">
                        <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 18.</note> enacted, <hi>That none ſhould be Juſtice of Aſſize,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>in the County where he was born, or did inhabit: Yet,</hi> ſaith the ſame judicious Lawyer, <hi>the King with a ſpecial</hi> non ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtante <hi>may diſpence with it, and gives the reaſon; for that it belongs to the inſeperable Prerogative of the King,</hi> viz. <hi>his power to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to ſerve.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſame
<note n="r" place="margin">
                        <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 18.</note> Lord Chief Juſtice, in the ſame report, is more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, and as full as if he had foreſeen this preſent Caſe of ours, where he affirms, <hi>That no Act can bind the King from any Prerogative, which is ſole and inſeperable to his perſon; but that he may diſpence with it by a</hi> non obſtante, <hi>and inſtanceth in the Sovereign Power to command any of his Subjects to ſerve him for the Public Weal. For this,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>is ſolely and inſeperably annexed to his Perſon, and this
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:99791:71"/>Royal Power cannot be reſtrained,</hi> continues he, <hi>neither in</hi> Theſi <hi>nor</hi> Hypotheſi, <hi>but that the King by his Royal Prerogative may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence with it:</hi> For all which he gives this moſt unanſwerable reaſon, <hi>becauſe upon the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment of the King, and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of the Subject, doth the Government ſubſiſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I might add very many more Authorities, as <hi>Edw.</hi> the Thirds repealing an Act of Parliament by Proclamation, as conſented to upon neceſſity: But I ſhall leave that to thoſe whoſe Province it is, and cloſe this Head with one Obſervation.</p>
                  <p>We are all commendably and juſtly tender of the preſerving the Liberties and Enfranchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments we enjoy, by the gracious Condeſcentions of our Princes, and are vigorous maintainers of our Properties; and ought we not to own, that there is as good reaſon, that the Kings of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
                     <pb n="136" facs="tcp:99791:72"/>ſhould be as ſolicitous to preſerve their Prerogatives which are their right? For as a moſt judicious
<note n="ſ" place="margin">Quicquid in Regali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus eſt Ita eſt Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipibus privatum ut Subditis quod ſuum eſt. Selden prefat. Mare Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum.</note> Antiquary and Lawyer expreſſeth, <hi>Whatſoever belongs to the Kings Royalty, he hath as much Propriety in it, as the Subject hath in any thing that is his.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We muſt likewiſe conſider, that the King is as much ſworn to preſerve the Right of his Crown, as the Liberties of the People: Therefore we find that branch in
<note n="t" place="margin">Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatis Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merata.</note> ſome Coronation Oaths, that the King ſwears <hi>he ſhall keep all the Lands, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, and Dignities of the Crown, righteous and free, in all manner whole, without any manner of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment: And the rights of the Crown, hurt, decay or loſt, to his power ſhall call again into the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Eſtate.</hi> Therefore my Lord
<note n="u" place="margin">12 Rep. 18</note> 
                     <hi>Coke</hi> praiſeth King <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the Second, in that he was a great Defender and Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainer
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:99791:72"/>of the Rights of the Crown.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Inferences from the premiſes.</note>Having diſpatched theſe Heads, I now come to the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of them, to the Teſt, which, as the Caſe now is, and ever will be ſo long as it ſtands unrepealed, deprives the King of the Allegiance of ſuch of his Subjects, as either Conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly or Deſignedly refuſe the taking of the Oaths, and affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Declaration enjoyned. The Inconveniency of which is double: Firſt, In robbing the King of ſo neceſſary and funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental a Right over his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, in commanding them to ſerve him in Offices Military and Civil, without which he is but a very Impotent Sovereign, and cannot exert that neceſſary Juſtice of Protecting, Reward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Imploying his Subjects, which ſurely is not only much to the diſhonour of the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign, but an unſufferable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:99791:73"/>And if
<note n="w" place="margin">31 <hi>Eliz. c.</hi> 4.</note> Imbezelling Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyning, and Conveying away the Arms, Ordnance, Muniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Shot, Powder, Habiliments of War, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is declared Fello<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; what ſort of Crime ſhall it be in any to withdraw him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from the Allegiance and Duty to his Sovereign, to ſerve him perſonally when he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands it?</p>
                  <p>This leads me to the Second, <hi>viz.</hi> the Subjects part, for this puts the Subject in a ſtate and condition either of diſability, or denying to ſerve his Sovereign at his pleaſure: for thoſe who are Roman Catholics cannot, while ſuch, take the Oaths and make the Declaration, they being ſo penned, that none of that Faith can own them without renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing their Church; the Act containing nothing in its own Nature eſſential to Obedience, but only controverted points of Faith.</p>
                  <pb n="139" facs="tcp:99791:73"/>
                  <p>So, many others who are not willing to ſerve the King in Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary and Civil Imployments, by pretext, that they cannot with a ſafe Conſcience take the Oaths, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Inſtantly obtain a Diſpenſation from their Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, which ought to be abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and unconditionate, and whatever may be the caſe of ſome few, may be of many; and conſequently a Prince may be deprived of the neceſſary Aid of his Subjects, even when any Rebellion or Invaſion ſhould happen; for tho the King be willing to diſpence with their not taking thoſe Oaths; <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yet they may inſiſt upon the penalty which they may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend they cannot be ſecured from.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Object."/> Here I muſt anſwer an Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection that I foreſee will be urged,
that <hi>Contra Hoſtem pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licum quilibet homo eſt miles,</hi> againſt a public Enemy every
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:99791:74"/>man ought to be a Soldier, and ſo it cannot be the intent of the Law, that the King ſhould be deprived of his Right to arm whom he pleaſeth and can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fide in, in ſuch a Conjuncture; but only it was deſigned to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Catholics from being Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſionated and Imployed in times of Peace.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Anſwer."/> But who ever peruſeth the Act,
will find no ſuch Excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or Limitation; which is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry rational plea againſt the equity of the Act, that taking away ſo great a Prerogative, makes no proviſion for the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Crown, even in ſuch caſes.</p>
                  <p>I remember my Lord <hi>Coke,</hi> ſpeaking of the ſtatute 11 <hi>H.</hi> 7. ſaith, <hi>It hath a flattering pream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, pretending to avoid many miſchiefs,</hi> yet it was found that by colour of it, <hi>Empſon</hi> and <hi>Dud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley,</hi> did many enormous things; therefore he obſerves that, <hi>When
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:99791:74"/>any Maxim, or Fundamental Law of the Realm is altered, it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible to foreſee what dangerous miſchiefs follow.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It becomes therefore all Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of the Monarchy of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> to be very careful to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the dangerous conſequences of taking out, or undermining any Corner Stone of that Royal Fabrick, and in this particular caſe to deliberate well of the dangerous ſequels of ſuch Laws as limit the Sovereign to uſe on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſons ſo and ſo qualified.</p>
                  <p>For by the ſame preſident, we cannot tell, if a Prince ſhould ſucceed that ſhall be a Calvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſt, or of any other perſwaſion oppoſite to the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and obtaine a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to his purpoſe, but that he may make renouncing of the Epiſcopal Government, or the Church of <hi>England,</hi> a conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on abſolutely neceſſary to ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitate any to ſerve in any pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:99791:75"/>Imployment, and then we ſhould find too late how cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious our Anceſtors ought to have been to conſider conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of things.</p>
                  <p>We have a freſh inſtance of this in the Kings Supremacy: which Act being purpoſely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to abridge the Popes pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er here in matters Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, hath heightned ſo much the Kings Power above what the Pope, or any other Eccleſiaſtical Court ever had; that now the Church of <hi>England</hi> finds how much they are at the Kings pleaſure, and muſt neceſſarily rely more upon the Kings cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency, than upon any ſecurity they are in, by that Act: So that if ſome men had conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the extent of this, it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable they would have acted with more caution and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:99791:75"/>
               <head>SECT. XIV. <hi>Concerning the Sanguinary and Penal Laws againſt Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholicks.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BEfore I proceed further, I think it neceſſary to ſpeak ſomething to the Sanguinary and Penal Laws againſt Roman Catholics; made upon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting the Pope's Supremacy in Eccleſiaſtical Matters, and for ſecuring the Sovereigns that were Proteſtants, and the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion eſtabliſhed ſince the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation.</p>
               <p>For the clear illuſtrating of which, I ſhall, 1ſt. Shew what the Principal of thoſe Laws were. 2ly. The grounds and reaſons why they were made. And, 3ly. Shew that as to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of the Civil Government, the ends for which they were
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:99791:76"/>made, now ceaſe; and then proceed to lay down the Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences that will attend the not repealing of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">An A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Penal Laws.</note>As to the firſt, In the 35 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 1. A Statute was made, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it is declared Treaſon in any who refuſe to take the Oath (commonly called of the Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy of <hi>H.</hi> 8. to diſtinguiſh it from that of Queen <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>) The perſons there appointed to take it, are to ſwear, that, <hi>Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the See nor the Biſhop of</hi> Rome, <hi>nor any foreign Poteſtate, hath, or ought to have any Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, Power, or Authority within the Realm,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Eliz.</hi>
                  </note>That of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>points all to ſwear, that, <hi>No foreign Prince, Perſon, Prelate, State, or Potentate, hath, or ought to have, any Juriſdiction, Power, Superiority, Prehemenency, or Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, Eccleſiaſtical or Spiritual, within the Realm:</hi> And in the 5th. of the Queen, the refuſers
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:99791:76"/>to take it, are guilty of a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munire. And in the former Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, <hi>No man ſhall by Writing, Printing, Teaching, Preaching,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>maintain, or defend the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, Preheminency, Power, or Juriſdiction, Spiritual or Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical, of any foreign Prince, Prelate, Perſon, State, or Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, which was heretofore clai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>within this Realm, for the third offence ſhall ſuffer as a Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 13 <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 2. It was Enacted, <hi>That if any perſon uſe or put in uſe, any Bull, Writing, or Inſtrument Written, or Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, of Abſolution or Reconciliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; or if any ſhall take upon them by colour of any ſuch Bull, Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>to Abſolve or Reconcile, any Perſon or Perſons, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe ſuch Abſolution, or Reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation, it ſhall be judged High Treaſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So, bringing of <hi>Agnus Dei's, Croſſes, Pictures, Beads, or ſuch
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:99791:77"/>like vain and ſuperſtitious things from the Biſhop or See of</hi> Rome, <hi>or any authorized, or claiming Authority from the Biſhop or See of</hi> Rome, <hi>to Conſecrate or Hallow the ſame, ſhall be guilty of a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>27 Eliz. c. 2. <hi>All Jeſuits, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minary Prieſts, or other ſuch Prieſts, Deacons or Religious, or Eccleſiaſtical Perſons whatſoever, born within the Queens Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons made, ordained, or profeſſed, by any Authority, or Juriſdicton, derived, challenged or pretended from the See of</hi> Rome (<hi>unleſs up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſome occaſions allowed by the Act) that ſhall be known to come into, or remain in the Realm or Dominions, ſhall ſuffer, loſe, and forfeit as in caſe of Treaſon: Alſo all ſuch as ſhall willingly, and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully receive, relieve, comfort, aid, or maintain any ſuch (being at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty and out of Priſon) ſhall be adjudged Fellons.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:99791:77"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Likewiſe to give or contribute any money, or other relief, to ſuch out of the Dominion, or for main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of any Colledge of Jeſuits or Seminary Prieſts, ſhall incur the penalty of Premunire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I need not mention the ſevere Laws of that Queen againſt convict Lay Recuſants: As con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fining them within five miles of their Habitation, and the poorer ſort that had none, to Priſons, or other Reſtraints; and to the end that <hi>the Realm be not peſtred and overcharged with the multitude of ſuch ſeditious and dangerous people, they muſt abjure the Realm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>King <hi>James</hi> the 1ſt 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 
                  <hi>Reg. c.</hi> 4. Confirms all the Laws of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> againſt Jeſuits, Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Prieſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and enjoyns the taking of the Oath of Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, commonly called Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, which was more directly to oblige to Fidelity, than in point of Faith, and only enjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to repair to Church, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:99791:78"/>there during the time of Divine Service, and not to ſend any to Seminaries beyond Seas.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 4.</note>But in the third of his Reign, when the Gun-powder Treaſon was diſcovered, the Laws were made more ſevere, that <hi>If any ſhall put in practice to abſolve, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade, or withdraw any of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the King, or of his Heirs from their Natural Obedience to his Majeſty, his Heirs, or Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, or to reconcile them to the Pope or See of</hi> Rome, <hi>it ſhall be High Treaſon, and thoſe that are willingly abſolved or withdrawn, as aforeſaid, or willingly reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, ſhall be adjudged Traitors.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 5.</note>At the ſame Parliament it was enacted,
that <hi>Recuſants ſhould not come to the Court, that they ſhould depart from</hi> London, <hi>be confined within five miles of their Habitations: Convict Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants ſhould be as Excommunicate Perſons, made incapable of moſt
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:99791:78"/>Offices Civil, or Military, of pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſing Law, Phyſick,</hi> &amp;c. Which no doubt gave riſe to the Teſt, and which in its full extent was never put in uſe, and hath been connived at, or diſpenſed with, under Proteſtant Princes ever ſince. Likewiſe under ſeveral pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties they were to <hi>Marry, Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, and Bury according to the Laws of the Realm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The grounds of theſe Laws.</note>Now if we enquire into the grounds of all theſe Laws,
we ſhall find them expreſſed in the ſeveral Acts, as in that of the 35<hi rend="sup">o</hi> of <hi>H.</hi> 8. it is ſaid to be made in Corroboration of that made in the 28th of the ſame King, <hi>To exclude the long uſurped Power, Authority, and Juriſdiction of the Biſhop of</hi> Rome.</p>
               <p>That of the firſt of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> is to the intent, <hi>That all uſurped and foreign Power, and Authority, Spiritual and Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, may for ever be clearly extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed, and never to be uſed or
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:99791:79"/>obeyed within this Realm,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>In the 5th of the ſame Queens Reign the grounds are expreſſed, <hi>For the avoiding both of ſuch hurts, perils, diſhonours, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences, as have before time befallen, as well to the Queens Majeſties Noble Progenitors, Kings of this Realm, as for the whole eſtate thereof, by means of the Juriſdiction and Power of the See of</hi> Rome, <hi>unjuſtly claimed and uſurped within this Realm, as alſo of the dangers by the fautors of the ſaid uſurped Power at this time grown to marvelous outrage, and licentious boldneſs, and now requiring more ſharp reſtraint and correction of Laws,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>The Reaſons for the paſſing the Act of the 13th of the ſame Queen,
is more full, <hi>viz. That divers ſeditious and very evil diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed people, minding not only to bring the Realm and the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Crown thereof (being indeed of it ſelf moſt free) into the
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:99791:79"/>Thraldom and Subjection, of that Foreign, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurped, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful Juriſdiction, Preheminency and Authority claimed by the See of</hi> Rome, <hi>but alſo to eſtrange, and alienate the minds and hearts of ſundry her Majeſties Subjects from their dutiful Obedience, and to raiſe and ſtir Sedition, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, within this Realm, and ſo mentions the Pope's Bull to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve and reconcile all thoſe that will be contented to forſake their due obedience, whereby hath grown great diſobedience and boldneſs in many, not only to withdraw, and abſent themſelves from all Divine Service, now moſt Godly ſet forth and uſed in this Realm, but alſo have thought themſelves diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of, and from all obedience, duty and allegiance to her Majeſty, whereby moſt wicked and unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Rebellion hath inſued, and to the further danger of this Realm for hereafter very like to be renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, if the ungodly and wicked at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:99791:80"/>in that behalf be not by ſeverity of Laws reſtrained and bridled.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 2.</note>The 27th of the ſame Queen lays no ſtreſs upon Religion,
but only on the ſecurity of the State, altho it was the firſt Act that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited Jeſuits &amp; Prieſts to come over and ſtay here, under pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty of Treaſon, without whoſe Offices, the Roman Catholics could no ways exerciſe their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: The grounds in that Act are expreſſed, <hi>That of late Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its, Prieſts,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>have come and been ſent into the Realm,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>of purpoſe, not only to withdraw her Highneſs Subjects from their due obedience to her Majeſty; but alſo to ſtir up and move Sedition, Rebellion, and open Hoſtility within the ſame,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 2.</note>The Act of the 35<hi rend="sup">o</hi> of that Queen expreſſeth,
that <hi>For the better diſcovery, and avoiding of ſuch traiterous and moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous conſpiracies and attempts, as
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:99791:80"/>are daily deviſed and practiſed againſt the Queen by ſundry wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſeditious perſons, who term<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves Catholics, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing indeed Spies and Intelligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>hiding their Deteſtable and Deviliſh Purpoſes, under a falſe pretext of Religion and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 4.</note>In the Act of the firſt of King <hi>James</hi> the firſt, the grounds are,
<hi>For the better and more due exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the Statutes heretofore made againſt Jeſuits, Seminary Prieſts, and other ſuch like Prieſts, as alſo againſt all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Recuſants, be it ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The third of the ſame King expreſſeth the Reaſons thus; <hi>For as much as it is found by daily experience, that many his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Subjects that adhere in their hearts to the Popiſh Religion, by the Infection drawn from thence, by the wicked and deviliſh counſels of Jeſuits, Seminaries,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:99791:81"/>and other like Perſons dangerous to the Church and State; are ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> far perverted in their Loyalties and due Allegiance unto the Kings Majeſty, and the Crown of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>as they are ready to entertain and execute any treaſonable conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racies and practices, as evidently appears by that more than barbarous and horrible attempt to have blown up with Gun-powder the King,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Having thus given a ſhort draught of the ſevere Laws againſt Roman Catholics, and the Reaſons and Grounds of them: It is obvious, that thoſe for the Supremacy were enact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed principally to exclude the Popes Authority in Matters Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical, which oppoſed King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth's Divorce, and the Reformation of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion begun: So that a Subject in point of Conſcience, and mere Matter of Faith, that could
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:99791:81"/>not be induced to believe a King and Prince capable of being Head of the Church; but ſhall be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincibly perſwaded (how erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious ſoever) that the Pope is St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Succeſſor, and Chriſts unqueſtioned Vicar upon Earth, and cannot, without hazard of his Soul, conſent to acknowledge otherwiſe; yet not withſtanding (by thoſe Laws) this invincible perſwaſion, without any other Crime, is interpreted High Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and puniſhed as ſuch; and Sir <hi>Thomas More</hi> Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor, the Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> and others, ſuffered death upon that account.</p>
               <p>In others of them, not only Prieſts, for receiving Orders ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Rites of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and coming over to Exerciſe the Office of their Function, but ſuch as were converted to the Romiſh Faith, or Reconciled, were involved in the Crime of Felony or Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:99791:82"/>without lifting an hand, uttering a Word, or imagin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the leaſt diſloyal thought againſt the peace of the Nation, where they were Subjects.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration how the grounds of thoſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verities now ceaſe.</note>Therefore firſt it muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, that ſince ſome of theſe Laws were made in the tender Age of the Reformation, when our Princes were very careful, that it might not be overlaid in its Swathing Cloaths: but now it is at a manly and maſterly growth and back-ſet with ſo numerous a Progeny and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful Abettors, that it can plead a preſcription and poſſeſſion ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to maintain it ſelf by Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument and Vote. Therefore we cannot now judge ſuch ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere Laws ſo neceſſary: there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no ſuch danger of the Popes exerciſing any other Supremacy here, than what is purely ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, over thoſe of that Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, in the Divine Offices of
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:99791:82"/>their Religion, without having any power to diſpoſe of any Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices, endow Religious Houſes, or eſtabliſh any Religious Polity over the Proteſtant Subjects: And as to any Temporal Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, it is impoſſible he ſhould receive any thing of that, which hath been ſo ſtrenuouſly oppoſed, even while the whole Nation, in Spirituals, ſubmitted to the Doctrine and Diſcipline of that Church: and I think all may be well ſatisfied, that our King is no ways diſpoſed to quit any of his Royal Prerogatives, or ſubject his Crown to any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Potentate upon Earth.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</note>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> It ought to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, that in Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi>'s time, there grew a ſtrong Faction in the State, by reaſon of the doubtful legitimacy of that Queen, as being by the Pope, and all Roman Catholics looked upon as born out of law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:99791:83"/>Wedlock, (her Fathers Wife Queen <hi>Catherine</hi> being then alive, and her Mother married to the King, before a legal Divorce, according to the Eccleſiaſtical Laws then in force) which oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned the Roman Catholics here, to be great Favourers and Abetters of <hi>Mary</hi> Queen of Scots; ſo that there was a poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical neceſſity in Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> and thoſe that adhered to her, (and upon that account were deſirous to preſerve the Proteſtant Religion ſhe em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced) with all the Art and Induſtry they could, by the ſevereſt Laws, to ſecure the one and the other; and by reaſon of ſeveral Attempts, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrections, and Forreign op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, the unfortunate Queen of Scots was put to death, for the ſafety of that Queen, which the Politicians of that Age thought could never be, as long as her Ryval lived.</p>
               <pb n="159" facs="tcp:99791:83"/>
               <p>Therefore we muſt look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe Laws as made moſtly for the ſecurity of the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reignty againſt Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lics, who, as ſuch, were ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged the greateſt Enemies to it: So that if we conſider the times when, and the perſons upon whom the bloodieſt Laws were executed; we ſhall find that they were principally, (if not only) when the State was either in real or imaginary dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger from ſuch: Whence it was, that the great States-man, the Lord <hi>Burleigh,</hi> publiſhed that Diſcourſe, <hi>That Papiſts were not put to death here for their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but for their Treaſons:</hi> Tho whoever conſiders how the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of the State and of the Religion was interwoven; will find it requires a ſubtil head to ſeparate them.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The grounds of them now ceaſe.</note>However the Caſe is now wholly altered, the Succeſſion of our King is not in the leaſt
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:99791:84"/>diſputable by Roman Catholics or Proteſtants; ſo that there can be no ground to keep up thoſe in force, for any other end, than the ſecuring the Proteſtant Religion only: So that we muſt invalidate all my Lord <hi>Burleighs</hi> Arguments, and bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom all our reaſoning upon Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, if we plead for thoſe Laws, which cannot fully be juſtified, but by avowing of that poſition, ſo much exploded by the Church of <hi>England, that Dominion is founded in Grace:</hi> which dangerous Doctrine, if it were once yielded, no Prince could be ſafe from thoſe that would alledge (and were power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful enough to prove it) that a Prince was not as holy as they, or of their Society; and where puniſhments, of the ſeverer kinds, are inflicted for different modes of Worſhip (where nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Immorality, Sedition, or Treaſon deſerve it, or it is not
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:99791:84"/>done with due reference to the peace and tranquility of the State) we muſt ground them on the ſame Principle, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſuch, and ſuch, are not Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers of the true Faith (which the preſent Rulers would infer they only had) muſt be cut off, or puniſhed, as Malefactors: Whereas it ſeems much more agreeable to Chriſtian Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the Rules of true Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy, that where any Church is legally ſettled, the care of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting miſchiefs ſhould be left to the Government, which no doubt would provide redreſs by ſuppreſſing Sedition, whereby none but ſuch as were Factious, Turbulent, and endanger the peace of the Government, might be under any preſſure, or forced to withdraw their effects, and forſake their Country, or to live in obſcurity and reſervedneſs, as people under the hatches: all which do manifeſtly impoveriſh
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:99791:85"/>a Country. However in our caſe it ſeems an unbecoming di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt of the intrinſick goodneſs of our Religion, or the ſtrength of our Arguments for it, when it muſt be defended by Club-law: And ſince we are out of all dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Roman Prieſts Trafficking for Forreign Invaſions (as when the ſevere Laws were made, the State was apprehenſive of) or of plotting and contriving a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; It is too great an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that the refuſing to take off the penal Laws, and that we do not acquieſce and yield to the moderate deſire of ſo gracious a King, is more out of an incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to gratifie Humor, and Contention, than for any other Cauſe. It being ſufficient that if ever ſuch a time ſhould oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curr, wherein the State ſhould be indangered by Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholics, the ſeverities might be reinforced.</p>
               <pb n="163" facs="tcp:99791:85"/>
               <p>When therefore we conſider, that the ſanguinary and penal Laws now in being, are ſevere to the utmoſt extremity: When a Turk or a Jew (not to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion other profeſſions more tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulent in a State) are not under any ſuch impending Laſh: And conſider what an after reckoning they may undergo, ſo that (the Laws ſtanding) not only Prieſts, and new Converts, but moſt of the old hereditary Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholics muſt be forced to flee, or abſcond themſelves. And as to the Teſt, however the King may, for his time, diſpence with the taking of it, and grant Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons to, and Indempnifie the not-takers of it, <hi>toties quoties;</hi> yet who ever ſhall act after the very laſt Pardon, may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed againſt under the next Proteſtant Succeſſor; and then it may be doubtful, whether the Kings diſpenſing Power will be allowed or not.</p>
               <pb n="164" facs="tcp:99791:86"/>
               <p>I ſay, if there were no other Reaſons; the King hath from hence ſufficient cauſe to inſiſt earneſtly upon the repealing theſe Laws and the Teſt; and it is probable, almoſt to a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration, that if this had been frankly granted, it would have ſatisfied the King, and have compoſed the minds of Roman Catholics, who, being placed in a condition of ſafety, would have continued that eſteem they had for the Church of <hi>England,</hi> ever ſince the late Civil Wars, when they were the only fellow-ſufferers.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <pb n="165" facs="tcp:99791:86"/>
               <head>SECT. XV. <hi>The Inconveniencies that will attend the not repealing of Penal Laws, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly the Teſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HAving premiſed this, I come to treat of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniencies, the denial of the repeal of theſe Laws brings with it: (<hi>viz.</hi>) Firſt, That it raiſeth in his Majeſties Royal Breaſt a prejudice againſt our Church and Religion; and the effects of the unkindneſs it may beget, appears to me of a much more dangerous conſequence, than the taking off the ſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary and penal Laws can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce: ſo that in ſtead of acting for the preſervation of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, we expoſe it, to more
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:99791:87"/>imminent and apparent danger, and inconſiderately run upon the Rock we would avoid; ſince ſuch unaccountable obſtinacy hath not only, in all probability, occaſioned the enquiry into the Kings Power in diſpenſing with the penal Laws, the diſplacing of Miniſters of State, and Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers in the Army, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſionating a greater number of Catholics than otherwiſe would have been admitted, the taking Catholic Lords into the Council, and granting the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion for Eccleſiaſtical Affairs; but may oblige the King to make ſtill greater Changes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt his Officers, Miniſters and Judges, than otherwiſe he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends: All thoſe holding their places only during his Royal Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, ſo that without violating any Law, he may at one ſtroke re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move moſt Proteſtant Officers from the Adminiſtration of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of State under him: And
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:99791:87"/>we know not what Changes and Alterations this wayward and unſeaſonable ſtiffneſs, may induce his Majeſty to make in the external Government and Polity of the Church, by the Power of his Supremacy and Prerogatives: And ſurely the extruding of Proteſtants from Power and Authority, either in Church or State, under the King, is likely to be a vaſter prejudice to our Religion, than the repealing the Teſt can be.</p>
               <p>Let us therefore think how much we are bound, even in Chriſtian prudence, for the ſake of our Religion, not to provoke the King to withdraw his Indulgence to us, in the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of that Religion, which he graciouſly offers to protect, and which Grace we ought not to requite by urging the keeping up thoſe ſeverities againſt thoſe of his Religion, which moſt Proteſtants would decline to
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:99791:88"/>execute, if they could, and which we cannot, if we would, until we firſt renounce obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to Gods Command, and Submiſſion to our Sovereign, by refuſing, if not overthrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Sacred Authority and Power: Whereas we are tyed by our Principles and Religion not to reſiſt, it being a chief and Eſſential Poſition and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> to render Active, and when we cannot do that, Paſſive Obedience to our Sovereign; and what ever we ſuffer, it will not excuſe us from the Guilt and Crime of indamaging and indangering our Religion, by this unneceſſary giving occaſion to it: when we might have ſaved, not only our Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of being moſt dutiful Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, but won ſo far upon the heart of our Royal Maſter, that it would have been in the power of none to have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtranged
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:99791:88"/>his Affections from us.</p>
               <p>The Spirit of moderation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh Chriſtians, and Calm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Diſcretion becometh Subjects in all dealing with their Sovereign; and we may be aſſured, that the greater in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitation we give our King by theſe Virtues, the greater aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurances we have of his Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of our Religion, and the preſervation of the preſent Peace, and Tranquility which we enjoy.</p>
               <p>Let us not therefore, by deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what we cannot hinder, loſe the greateſt Bleſſings, and Happineſſes we may retain, that King and People may live in that happy and good under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, which may continue, and Crown the ſweetneſs and eaſineſs of his Royal Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment over us, and of our Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility, Proſperity and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs under his Shadow.</p>
               <pb n="170" facs="tcp:99791:89"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience.</note>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Till theſe Laws be taken off, it will continue thoſe moſt dangerous of Evils, that can befal the King and People, when there is no good correſpondence betwixt the King, and the two Houſes of Parliament.</p>
               <p>On the Kings part, <hi>firſt,</hi> we may call to mind the miſerable times of King <hi>John,</hi> and King <hi>Henry</hi> the third, and thoſe more freſh and never to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got under King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt. <hi>Secondly,</hi> However prudent and wiſe a Prince may be, yet the watchful envy or deſigns of ſome Neighbour Potent Prince or State, may neceſſitate our King to defend his Merchants, or Plantations, to ſuccour his Allies, or to ſecure his People from Damage or Hoſtilities, whereby he may be forced to have recourſe to his Parliament for Aid, which, while a good correſpondence is wanting, may render them ſlow to grant, or
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:99791:89"/>upon unequal Conditions. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> This will give an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to all ſorts of Male-Contents, and Enemies to the Monarchy to beſtir themſelves, to embroil, and ferment the People into ſome dangerous De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, Sedition or Rebellion.</p>
               <p>On the Peoples ſide, the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs that will befall us by this want of a good underſtanding betwixt the King and his two Houſes, will be, firſt, that ſince our King by a mature Age, and a great Experience of all affairs relating to Arms and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is fitted and enabled more than moſt of his Royal Predeceſſors to aggrandize him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and give renown to his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, by buoying up whatever hath been ſunk in the reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the World: And is able to increaſe the Traffick of his people, and inlarge their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, and his Empire, and make as great a Figure in the
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:99791:90"/>World as any Crowned Head. All the Bleſſing, we and our Neighbours might expect from ſo qualified a Prince, will be utterly loſt; ſo that in ſtead of tranſporting his Cares, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels and Arms into foreign parts, he ſhall be neceſſitated to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine them within the Circle of his own Dominions, only to keep them from Sedition or any worſe miſchief: So that the hopeful opportunities, which the World knows our King might have to hold again the Ballance of Europe, and make us as flouriſhing a people as ever, will be totally loſt: To the great ſatisfaction, no doubt, of ſome of his Neighbours, and the general and irreparable loſs to us and our Poſterity, who with ſad reflections may lament the occaſion of this diſpute.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Such a want of good Correſpondence betwixt the King and his two Houſes, will
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:99791:90"/>hinder us from obtaining ſuch advantageous Laws, for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the Subjects, as, this Remora being removed, might rationally be expected; among which, moſt probably, one or more; might be a Corroborati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Kings Gracious Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of protecting the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and whatever elſe the two Houſes might find uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for the public good.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> This Non-correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence muſt gratifie and incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage all the Enemies to Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, and all thoſe who were for the Bill of Secluſion; this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord being the only pleaſing Harmony to them, who never hug themſelves with ſo full an <hi>Ohe!</hi> of content and ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, as when they find the Crown in any ſtraits; or can foment (if not conjure up) a Spirit of Jealouſie betwixt the King and his Parliament, and when they have ſtolen the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:99791:91"/>Hearts from the King, they are upon the Tiptoes of hope, that they may ſtrike in for the prize.</p>
               <p>If we have not a feeling ſenſe of the miſerable ſtate, that Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition and Rebellion (It's moſt ſavage Elder Brother) will bring us all to, let us conſult our bloody Annals, and our An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors deplorable experience, and then ponder well whether it be <hi>Tanti,</hi> to move Heaven and Earth, harras our Country, and embrue it with the blood of ſo many of our Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and neareſt Relations, and at laſt fight our ſelves into a much worſe condition, than we are ever like to be in by grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Repeal; which in this juncture is moſt reaſonable, if not for our Kings ſake, and the Roman Catholics; yet at leaſt for our own peace and tranqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and the eſtabliſhing our hopes of his Majeſties kindneſs to our Church.</p>
               <pb n="175" facs="tcp:99791:91"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The laſt Inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience.</note>The laſt Reaſon I ſhall urge, is, that the refuſing to Vacate theſe Acts may neceſſitate the King to grant a Toleration, which, of all things, the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> hath hitherto moſt dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and to which we may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the King is well enough in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined out of a principle of cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency to his people in general, as well as Indulgence to his Catholic Subjects; which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho his Royal Brother (after an eſſay) at the earneſt ſolicitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Parliament, was Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly pleaſed to recal, to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the Church of <hi>England,</hi> yet we cannot expect that our King (not having thoſe motives, and being courted by ſo many to grant it, and finding the exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his Supremacy) will think it his Intereſt to revoke it if he once eſtabliſh it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Roman Catholics, and other Diſſenters from the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </note>Here it will not be a miſs to
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:99791:92"/>conſider, the great difference there is betwixt Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lics and other Diſſenters, while the Laws are in force: The Non-conformiſts may meet to the number of Five, beſides the Family, and have their Paſtor, or Teacher with them, and the diſagreeableneſs betwixt them and the Church of <hi>England</hi> is not ſo great, but that thoſe who have Eſtates, or deſire to obtain Offices of honour or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit (even to do the Crown a diſſervice, as we found in thoſe that were to capacitate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be Sheriffs in the late times) could readily Conform. Whereas Roman Catholics are in extream peril from the very harbouring their Prieſts: ſo that in this the Roman Catholics are in a ſadder ſtate than any Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians are: For to exerciſe their Religion without Prieſts, for performing the Office of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing, Adminiſtring the <hi>Bleſſed
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:99791:92"/>Sacrament,</hi> burying the Dead, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Is in that Church (and ought to be in all others) impoſſible, and to have them for celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting theſe and other Divine Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices (as the Laws now are) renders them obnoxious to the puniſhments inflicted on Felons and Traytors; and there is no poſſibility of the Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lics, as ſuch, conforming even ſo much as in going once a month to Church, without putting themſelves out of the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of their Church, which, with them, is to be avoided more than the utmoſt ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</p>
               <p>When therefore we conſider the Unchriſtianneſs of ſuch ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere Laws under our circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, and reflect that tho the greateſt part of the diſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets, from the Tenth Year at leaſt of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> have ariſen from the pretences of keeping out Popery, and the Advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:99791:93"/>the Long Parliament had againſt King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, was from that ſource, and the troubles of our late merciful King, were bottomed on the ſame apprehenſions; and yet now that we ſee it's actually pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed, we find no ſuch dreadful events; but that the Vizard was portraied much more terrible than now when it appears with open face; and now, when we ſee the publick exerciſe of the Roman Catholic Religion, we only find it gazed at as a Novel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but no affrightments attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it; and we find, what we underſtand in Sermons and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techizing is Chriſtian and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, and what we underſtand not in Ceremonies, we ſee full of Pomp and Magnificence, and further we ſee not.</p>
               <p>I ſay, when we conſider all this, and that it is in our choice, whether we will allow the ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinary and penal Laws to be
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:99791:93"/>aboliſhed with a ſecurity in the exerciſing the Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; or on the contrary, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniencies before recited, and a Tolleration to boot; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks it ſhould be no difficult matter to determine which were more advantagious.</p>
               <p>Having thus ſhewn ſome of the diſadvantages to Us and our Religion, by the refuſal of a Repeal: I might propoſe the advantages which will accrue by yielding up thoſe Laws the King hath ſuch an obligation in Honour and Juſtice (at leaſt in his own Royal Apprehenſion) to inſiſt upon, but that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moval of the one, puts the other in their place.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <pb n="180" facs="tcp:99791:94"/>
               <head>SECT. XVI. <hi>The practicableneſs of Roman Catholics and Proteſtants living under one Secular Government.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THerefore I ſhall chuſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſhew the practica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs of Roman Catholics and Proteſtants living in the full enjoyment of their reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Religions, under Princes of either Religion: And firſt ſhall obſerve, that the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Church of <hi>England</hi> are the two Churches (in <hi>Europe</hi> at leaſt) that are the moſt conſpicuous and of moſt renown: Both plead for the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity of their Doctrine: The Roman Catholics are of one Communion, and ſo is the Church of <hi>England;</hi> but Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtantiſm at large takes in a
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:99791:94"/>greater variety of ſubdiviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and thoſe ſeparate from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as much as that doth from the <hi>Roman.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> It hath been the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour of many learned and pious men, to accommodate the points in difference betwixt Roman Catholics and Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants. But by reaſon of ſecular intereſts, no expedient could be found to adjuſt them, till at laſt in Germany (from whence our <hi>Saxon</hi> Anceſtors came) af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter about twenty years war, wherein the Country was the very Theatre on which the moſt Tragical Effuſion of Blood, and the moſt depopulating waſte, by Fire and Rapine, were acted to the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of humane cruelty and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge; and all this principally upon the account of the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies and Proteſtants, upon ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:99791:95"/>of their Religion, and being at laſt throughly wearied with the unſucceſsful attempts upon one another, in the year 1624. they came to the following ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlements, which, I believe, they hitherto reap the fruit of, being confirmed <hi>Anno</hi> 1648. at the Treaty of <hi>Munſter,</hi> whereby it was made an Imperial Law.</p>
               <p>The Duke of <hi>Newburgh</hi> is a ſtrict Roman Catholic, yet in his Country of <hi>Juliers,</hi> even at <hi>Deuſeldorp,</hi> the principal place of his reſidence (not to name other Towns) Lutherans and Calviniſts have their Churches as well as Roman Catholics, and I ſuppoſe he allows the like liberty in the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> as the Count <hi>Palatine</hi> did, to whom he lately ſucceeded as his heir male.</p>
               <p>The Duke of <hi>Brandenburg</hi> is himſelf a Calviniſt, yet his Subjects are for the moſt part Lutherans, and in ſome parts
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:99791:95"/>of his Dominions Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholics freely enjoy their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
               <p>The Biſhop of <hi>Mentz</hi> (tho a Roman Catholic) admits the Lutherans in his City of <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> to exerciſe their way of worſhip.</p>
               <p>So the Duke of <hi>Saxony,</hi> a Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theran, hath eſtabliſht ſuch an accord in his City of <hi>Budifin,</hi> that the Roman Catholics, and Lutherans celebrate their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Offices, in the very ſame Church, ſeparated only by a Grate.</p>
               <p>The Biſhop of <hi>Oſnaburgh</hi> (of the Houſe of <hi>Zell</hi>) is himſelf a Lutheran; yet in his Town, from whence he hath his Title, both Roman Catholics and Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans have their Churches: and the next Biſhop muſt be a Catholic, and ſo Alternately. And the Lutheran Canons ſay their Offices, with the Catholics in the Cathedral.</p>
               <pb n="184" facs="tcp:99791:96"/>
               <p>In the City of <hi>Ausburgh</hi> they have two chief Magiſtrates, whereof one muſt always be a Roman Catholic, and the other a Lutheran.</p>
               <p>The Prince of <hi>Sulzback</hi> is a Roman Catholic, by profeſſion; yet in ſome parts of his Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, not only Roman Catholics and Lutherans enjoy their diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent worſhip, but interchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably the ſame day, in the ſame place: The Roman Catholics uſing a portable Altar, which they place upon the Lutheran Altar, when they officiate.</p>
               <p>The Abbot of <hi>Curvey</hi> is a Prince of the Empire, and a Roman Catholic, and hath ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Villages in his Juriſdiction, whereof ſixteen are Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholics, only <hi>Anſted</hi> hath Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran Inhabitants, who enjoy their Religion, and in their Annual Proceſſion, not only thoſe Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans, but the Envoys from the Lutheran Princes of <hi>Brunſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick,
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:99791:96"/>Lunenburgh,</hi> and <hi>Hannover</hi> attend it, ſome carrying the Abbot's Mitre, others the Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier <hi>(&amp;c.)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At <hi>Lambſpring,</hi> under the Rule of the Biſhop of <hi>Hilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhem,</hi> the Abbot and Convent are principal Lords, yet they permit the Lutherans to have a Church.</p>
               <p>Thus the Germans live in neighbourly Love and Amity, and buſie not themſelves in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiring one anothers ruin.</p>
               <p>There is one great inſtance in this part of <hi>Germany,</hi> that comes home to our Caſe. The late Duke of <hi>Hannover,</hi> being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted to the Roman Faith, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his Father, the Duke of <hi>Zell</hi>'s Life, lived out of his Country, and was a Canon at <hi>Paris;</hi> and tho he lived in a low Station with few Servants; yet he kept ſuch a correſpondence with perſons of Quality, in his Fathers Juriſdiction, that tho
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:99791:97"/>his Father deſigned to diſinhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit him; yet upon the news of his laſt Sickneſs he poſted into the Confines, and upon notice of his Death at <hi>Hannover</hi> (where his Elder Brother was) he poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Zell,</hi> and was ſo well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived there, that he was ſoon in the Head of a conſiderable Army, and by mediation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the two Brothers, he made an exchange of <hi>Zell,</hi> the nobler Dukedom, for that of <hi>Hanno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,</hi> the richer; where being ſetled, he governed his Country very peaceably for fourteen years, and contented himſelf with a Chappel for his own Devotion, and a Convent of Capuchins near it; and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcuouſly employed Roman Catholics and Lutherans in his Military and Civil Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, giving to his Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholic Subjects free liberty of the Exerciſe of their Religion, and wrought ſo good an accord
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:99791:97"/>among his Subjects, of both Perſwaſions, that there were no animoſities among them, none repining at anothers prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but in point of Duty and Allegiance, they all reſpected, honoured and ſerved him, and lived happily under his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and he was in as good eſteem among his Lutheran Subjects, as any Prince had been long before.</p>
               <p>He dying without Iſſue, <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nover</hi> fell to his younger Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Biſhop of <hi>Oſnabourgh,</hi> who is a Temporal Prince, not in holy Orders, but married; and hath ſeveral Princes and Princeſſes his Children, and is himſelf a Lutheran. Upon his entrance to his Principality he did not proſecute the Roman Catholics; only the Capuchins, who lived upon Alms, could not ſtay as in a Convent, tho he profered them protection for their perſons, and Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholics
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:99791:98"/>enjoy the liberty, I have before mentioned, as others do in ſeveral Principalities in <hi>Germany:</hi> Whether this Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony happen by reaſon the people are not ſuch Zealots in Religion, as in other places, to be cutting of Throats for it, I cannot tell; but I am ſure it is a great eaſe to Prince and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
               <p>By this Example, I hope it will appear, how practicable it is, that Roman Catholics and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants may live under the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of Magiſtrates of either Belief, without ſwallowing up one another; and if it were not for the violent prejudices which ſome have, there is no need of endeavours to extirpate Roman Catholics, who being few in number, yet are conſiderable in quality and intereſt: Nor of overſetting the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> whoſe true Members ever have been Loyal, and in the
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:99791:98"/>worſt of times have joyned with Roman Catholics for the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of the Crown, and have been fellow-ſufferers.</p>
               <p>Surely we cannot forget the time when ſo great a Credit was given to a Plot, which (even as it was publiſhed in Narratives) was as dark and confuſed, as the <hi>Chaos;</hi> as mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous as any Figment of the Poets, or in the Alcharon; full of impoſſibilities, and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions; So that it is now our wonder and aſtoniſhment, how greedily it was ſwallowed: Yet this ſerved the turn to exaſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the people, yea the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it ſelf, to that degree, that not only the Catholics were branded as the moſt trayterous, barbarous, cruel, bloody-minded Men in the World; but they ſuffered the ſeverities of the Laws: And much inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent blood was ſhed upon the Teſtimony of a few perjur'd
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:99791:99"/>Villans, who got the Character of the Kings Evidence; yet we cannot but remember who They were, that while they were fixing our Eyes ſo intently, upon the defence of the Kings Perſon, and the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> againſt the Plots of Papiſts, were in the mean time pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding their Blunderbuſſes, and deſigning a moſt horrid Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicide.</p>
               <p>I recal this to mind only to evince, that we are not to look upon Papiſts, through the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectives have been hitherto af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded us; but to believe our own Eyes, and other Organs of Sence, and conſider whether a Popiſh Succeſſor be ſuch a Creature, yea, a Fiend, as he was repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <pb n="191" facs="tcp:99791:99"/>
               <head>SECT. XVII. <hi>The Character of his Majeſty.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF I were able to furniſh my ſelf with as much Celeſtial Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumination and Spirit from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, as the Author of that Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter fetched from the Mines of Fire and Brimſtone below; I ſhould not be able to deſcribe, as I ought, any tolerable ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude of our great Sovereign, whoſe Portraicture the pannick fears, luxurious ſpite, and hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh deſigns of ſome then ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed.</p>
               <p>Yet with humble Submiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Reverence due to the Majeſty of ſo great a King, I think it neceſſary to give ſome
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:99791:100"/>faint touches of thoſe out-lines, which ought to ſtrike us all with Admiration and Joy.</p>
               <p>It will, I doubt not, be readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly owned, that his Majeſty is indowed with as large a portion of thoſe Royal and Princely Virtues (which ſignalize great Monarchs, and render them conſpicuous) as any Prince that hath governed theſe Realms for many years: And, without flattery, we cannot but admire his Courage, Reſolution, and Promptneſs of Mind, Active<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, delight in Buſineſs, thorough inſpection into his Affairs, with ſuch a peculiar ſweetneſs and benignity of temper, as, ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are of great value in Crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Heads; much more, when, to ſuch a degree and luſtre, they are mingled with Juſtice, Honour, Fortitude, Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and other Heroick Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:99791:100"/>in a Conſtellation: ſo that even thoſe, who moſt paſſionate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wiſh him the Delight and Darling, as well as Glory of his People; can ſuperadd no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to their wiſhes, but that he were of their Religion. But in the Judgment of Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholics, he finds, not only an eſteem due to the accumulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his illuſtrious Virtues, but is inriched with a Ray more, by the profeſſion of his Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>Thoſe, who are bleſſed Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of his familiar Diſcourſes, admire the ſerenity of his Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor: few Mortals being leſs clouded, or ſhaken with any ſtorm of paſſion. Thoſe are witneſſes how he imploys his dreſſing time, in enquiries af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter what is remarkable in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moteſt Countries, whether they
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:99791:101"/>relate to Government, Peace or War, Situation, and Fortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of places, correſpondencies one with another, Cuſtoms and Uſages, Diſpoſition of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and their Commodities, and of Traffick, or the perſonal Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and Accompliſhments of great Men: The Inventers of uſeful Arts, eſpecially ſuch as reſpect Military Diſcipline, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigation and Traffick; mingling his own choice Obſervations, which render all his Diſcourſes pleaſing, yea, ſometimes ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſing, and always profitable and inſtructive.</p>
               <p>Never was any Princes Court freer from debauchery, and more orderly in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>poſal of all Officers in it, from whence the Sovereign Maſter's ſolid Rules and exemplarineſs are notably diſcover'd. The Diligent, Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous,
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:99791:101"/>Sober, Ingenious and Loyal, are received without cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of their Religion: The Sloathful, Turbulent, Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, Debauched and Irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious are as much diſcouraged, as is moſt manifeſt by bis ſevere charges againſt Swearing and Drunkenneſs (<hi>&amp;c.</hi>)</p>
               <p>Paſs we thence to his Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, we cannot but obſerve, with ſome aſtoniſhment, how his public Devotions are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed with a ſerious Attenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and a Fervour and Zeal equal to thoſe that officiate at the Altar.</p>
               <p>When we conſider the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of his Revenues, by his own peculiar Wiſdom and Direction, we cannot but be amazed at that vaſt Capacity; which thoſe, bred to the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment,
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:99791:102"/>cannot equal no more than they can, that inſpection into all the Officies of his great Empire, the Uſes and Abuſes of which are as well known to him, as any Nobleman knows his Surveys, Rentals and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices; what a Fatigue would this give to the ableſt of his Subjects, to order ſome few par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars of theſe Matters, much more to ſuperintend the whole as he doth.</p>
               <p>Did we ſurvey the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful increaſe of ſtores he hath made, for all ſorts of Muniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, both for Land and Sea, we ſhould think he imployed his Care, and a great part of his Revenues in nothing elſe: But when we attend him to his Camp and Navies, we find a new Charge, a new Care.</p>
               <pb n="197" facs="tcp:99791:102"/>
               <p>His Majeſties extraordinary Diligence and Skill in diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plining his Army, and the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection he hath brought it to in one year, will be as incredible to after Ages, as it is the wonder of this. It is the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of ſome, that have ſeen other Princes Troops, that (conſidering their number) they exceed all others, not only in the richneſs of the Clothes of the Officers and the Guards; the neatneſs of the Common Soldiers, the goodneſs of their Arms, the ſightlineſs of the Men and Horſes, the order of the Camp; but in the Skill in all their Exerciſes, their readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to obſerve Orders, and the Civility and Morals of them; being free from thoſe Debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheries, which effeminate and unfit Soldiers for Valor and Vigilance: And no Prince can
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:99791:103"/>take more effectual ways, by due and conſtant pay, and proviſion of all things neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, to oblige his Troops to Fidelity and Courage, Skill and Reſolution, than his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty doth; ſo that his Camp is not only accompliſhed in Military Matters, but is a nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery of good Education: It being his Majeſties ſpecial Command, that the Soldiers ſo behave themſelves in the Country, that they may not only be regarded as his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, wearing his Livery, but as their Guard, and the ſecurity of their peace and quiet. So that none can juſtly repine at their numbers, but ſuch as would be glad to ſee him deſtitute of any force that might hinder their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivances againſt his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <pb n="199" facs="tcp:99791:103"/>
               <p>We have already ſeen his Majeſties Troops, and we now find, with how great eare and diligence he is equipping his Fleet, which we may be ſure will be anſwerable to the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice he intends them for, and proportionable to that Method and Order of his Land Forces: and then, no doubt, it will exceed what former Ages have known, when they are fitted by ſo great and magnanimous a Prince, that hath ſo long been Lord High Admiral him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
               <p>Theſe things have milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Witneſſes: But who can divine the Royal Solicitude and Care, and thoſe wiſe Contrivances, for the good of his people, which are the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of his retired hours in his
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:99791:104"/>Cloſet: There, where he revolves in his Great Mind, how to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all the Inſtruments of his Power, to ſet all the Wheels of this great Machin on work, to conſider who are fitted for every diſtinct under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking; how to allott the thinking, grave and wiſe, the contriving part: And the bold, and obedient, the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutive part of his Affairs. There he ruminates of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors Wiſdom and Addreſs, and what is fit to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to them. Here he conſults the ſafety, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, and wealth of his Subjects; how to make all of Loyal Principles (tho of different perſwaſions in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion) live at eaſe and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. Here he ſtudies to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viate the deſigns of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctious and Seditious, which
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:99791:104"/>give greateſt diſquiet to the otherwiſe flouriſhing Reigns of Princes: To reward, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance and honour thoſe who do him the acceptableſt Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices. Here he bears the Burthen of his Kingdoms a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, revolves the fate of other Empires, and reſoves the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del of his own.</p>
               <p>May the Divine Wiſdom inſpire his Royal Breaſt here, and in all places, to follow ſuch Methods, as may make his People truly Reverence, Love, and dutifully Obey him, whereby not only his Reign may be proſperous and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, but our Poſterity may find the good effects of his Government.</p>
               <p>Were his Majeſties Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter as well known, through
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:99791:105"/>all his Dominions, as it is to thoſe neareſt to him, (how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever imperfectly I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed it) I ſhould not think it poſſible that any could en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain ſuch Umbrages of fear of his Conduct, ſince we may be aſſured ſo wiſe, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarily qualified a Prince, will attentively conſider how his own eaſe and felicity is involved in that of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects.</p>
               <p>Were he a Prince leſs Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous, and Active in his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, (which his Princely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes and temperance contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute ſo much to) were he leſs experienced in a long Tract of Obervations, leſs knowing of men, and of their by-paſt, and preſent, innate and forced diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions; and of a leſs piercing Judgment, and vivacity of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: Had he not ſo many times
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:99791:105"/>adventured his Life for the Honour and Safety of theſe Kingdoms; were he a Prince that did not ſo ſeriouſly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countenance prophaneneſs and vice, or gave not ſuch ſignal tokens of his piety; were he a Prince that devolved his Cares on others, whereby he might enjoy a pompous and eaſie life; were he not conſtant to his purpoſes, or were leſs exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary in all provident mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery, or ſparing in the expence of Proviſions for the Honour and Safety of his Dominions; Were he ſubject to any tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſport of Paſſion, or eaſily im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon by ſlie and cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Achitophels;</hi> we might ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect his concern for his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and think him negligent or not underſtanding of his Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt. But a Prince endowed with ſo extraordinary qualifications
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:99791:106"/>can never be wanting in the great concern of his Royal Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, both in conſerving his Dominions in peace, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing indulgent to all, that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily diſtruſt not his Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Intentions, and make not falſe conſtructions, comments, and gloſſes upon them, and by an unworthy waywardneſs court cloudy weather or ſtorms, when they might enjoy ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine and a clear sky.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
               <pb n="205" facs="tcp:99791:106"/>
               <head>SECT. XVIII. <hi>The Concluſion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TO draw now towards a Concluſion, I ſhall only offer you ſome conſiderations, which I deſire you will ſeriouſly think upon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> you cannot but have obſerved, that there are a ſet of men, who although they be at as great a diſtance from knowing his Majeſties Reſolves, as they are from the Moon; yet will pretend to have Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſcopes in Politicks, whereby they can diſcover all the Hills and Valleys, Seas and Rolling Sands, the Precipices and
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:99791:107"/>Plains, the Deſarts and Fertil Champaigns of our little world, and by engraffing Microſcopes upon them, can magnifie to what prodigious bulk they pleaſe, Molehills and the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuteſt Inſects: Yea they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to diſcover the ſecret Springs and Movements of all Counſels, and that, (which is their greateſt dexterity) by a Charm they have, they can make every one they get to uſe theſe, to believe the reality of what they repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</p>
               <p>Theſe men conſidering the Kings Perſonal Reſolution, Courage and Conduct, and the Noble Deſigns he decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at his firſt entrance on his Government, that, by the bleſſing of God he would ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture his perſon as far as
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:99791:107"/>any man in his Dominions for the good of his people, and endeavour to raiſe the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown and repute of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as high as any of his Predeceſſors: and withall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the ſucceſs that had attended all his undertakings, knew that they could no ways foreſlow the progreſs of his affairs, but by depriving him of the Cordial Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his Proteſtant Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects.</p>
               <p>Therefore finding that his Majeſty would be bound in Honour and Juſtice to ſhew favour to Catholicks in im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploying them and endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a repeal of penal Laws, and knowing how much it would ſtand them in hand to lay hold of this opportunity; fell preſently to ſigh out their
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:99791:108"/>extream fears, that the Church of <hi>England</hi> was to be trod under foot, if not totally ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpated.</p>
               <p>They knew full well, that as a Nipping Froſt ſuddenly diſpoyleth freſh Flowers of their richeſt paint and beauty, and makes their erecteſt leaves ſoften and flag, and ſinges the talleſt Oaks, as well as the lower Thickets and Copices; even ſo from this chilling ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, the briskeſt and moſt active Loyalty of ſome would be palſied, benummed, or cramped; a Cloudy Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie would ſeize others, and it would ſlacken the ſails, and becalm, and make thoſe Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels Hull and float in a dead Sea, that had formerly made ſo fair a progreſs towards the Port of Loyalty.</p>
               <pb n="209" facs="tcp:99791:108"/>
               <p>They knew likewiſe, that if they could get the Kings deſires oppoſed in Parliament, it would effectually hinder the former good Correſpondence had been betwixt the King and them, and ſo it was their Intereſts, like cunning Ambo-dexters, to animate, and incourage the Kings Zeal for it, and at the ſame time to ſet all other tools at work to get it oppoſed.</p>
               <p>This was the maſter-piece of ſome peoples policy, which poſſibly was not all home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, and it hath moſt pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfully effected the buſineſs: and no doubt but it was ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to have been prognoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated.</p>
               <p>However the matter hath been managed, it is too late
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:99791:109"/>to call back yeſterday: The King hath the ſame motives to inſiſt upon the taking off the penal Laws; and ſince I have laid down ſo fully the reaſons and inconveniencies of denying his deſire: It will be very becoming the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the Parliament (as Loyal as a Prince can wiſh) and of all the true members of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and of all that deſire, we and our poſterity may be happy, to ſtudy ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedients, as there may not be eternal heart-burning, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions, jars, and feuds, betwixt the Members of the two ſo Famous Churches, and that they will not only impartially conſider what I write to you, but that they will call in the aids of their Chriſtianity, reaſon and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:99791:109"/>to govern their Actions, that we may not endanger our Religion, or be miſled by falſe fires, and trained into thoſe denns, where de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and ſlavery keep their reſidence, and where the pretended qualm at the apprehenſion of their dying Religion, is but to get a doſe of that Volatile Salt of Vipers, that they hope would raiſe to life again their good Old Cauſe.</p>
               <p>I know it is one of the difficulteſt cures to bring Hypocondriac people to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon, or forget their complaints: If they get a notion by the fore-top, they ſwing it about, as boys do fire-ſticks, till it appears a whole Circle of Fire, whereas ſix drops
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:99791:110"/>of water will quench it. Sometimes ſuch are cured with Hellibore, but oftner by calm reaſoning, divert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their thoughts, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting the ill conſequences of ſuch groundleſs phancies, and then cordial refreſhings of their ſpirits bring them to compoſure.</p>
               <p>I have made choice only of the laſt, and deſire all Lovers of their Country, yea, and of their Religion alſo, to conſider what the deſigns of ſome men are, by their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, wherein they endeavour to poſſeſs the Souldiery with ſtrange apprehenſions, and would poyſon them in their principles of Allegiance. Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it can be to no other end, but that they hope thereby to diſarm them of their Loyalty,
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:99791:110"/>and ſo to find from them little reſiſtance, when they could be able (by ſetting up the Standard of Proteſtantiſm) to aſſemble their power againſt the Government.</p>
               <p>Have you not ſeen other Libels for ſetting up Stipula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, Conditional Monarchy? There was never an Inſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, or any Inteſtine Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but it was occaſioned by a prepoſſeſſion of the people, with an ill opinion of the Princes Conduct, and by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauching of the people in their duty; and when there was either a faction in the State, or diverſity in Religion, theſe readily divided their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herence, either to the Crown, or to the Seditious, or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels. But whoever got by ſuch commotions, I am ſure the
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:99791:111"/>generality of the Subjects were ſufferers; and whenever God Almighty puniſhed them in this kind, yet we find, in the upſhot, the Government was again ſetled more firm, as we may learn even by our lateſt examples at the Reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of King <hi>Charles</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond; And whoever conſider the benefits that accrue to a people that live quietly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Government, and the ſad miſchiefs that Faction and Sedition cauſe, will chuſe the one rather than the other, and will find that all the ſtricter impoſitions on the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, have been occaſioned by the peoples diſobedience, and the diſplacing of Officers have been for the ſecurity of the Government: Hence the Act of purgeing Corporations, and the late Quowarranto's, and
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:99791:111"/>ſome Acts of State of later date.</p>
               <p>Diſtruſt of a Princes good Intentions for his People, and diffidence in his gracious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, above all things are to be avoided in Subjects. It is that hinders them from yeild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his reaſonable deſires. Our gracious King hath mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied his Aſſurances of his protection of our Religion, and it is our Duty and Intereſt to be confident in, and truly thankful for them, and neither by inſolency, miſtruſt, or pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhneſs to forfeit his Royal Favour.</p>
               <p>Thoſe who are well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the gracious and generous temper of his Majeſty, know, that a diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in his Sacred Promiſes,
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:99791:112"/>is ſo much the more diſobliging, as it is the queſtioning his ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racity, which is one of the chief and moſt valuable of his Royal Virtues. This diſtruſt touching ſo vital a part, as the Juſtice and Reputation of any private perſon, raiſeth a deep reſentment: how much more muſt it be ill indured in ſo great a Perſon, who hath that peculiar temper of Spirit (ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to his Birth and Dignity) not to ſuffer his Methods to be thwarted, or diſputed; eſpecially where the conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions put upon them, tend to the diminution of the Love and Honour his Subjects owe him, and will occaſion ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious withdrawing of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects from their Duty and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance? which as they are moſt important miſchiefs, and hazard the Peace of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:99791:112"/>ſo they have, in all humane probability, been the rrue, and only Motives, that have induced his Majeſty to withdraw his wonted kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs from ſome perſons, that I am confident out of mere inadvertency of theſe conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences, and out of deſire to ſerve him in other Methods, have fallen under his diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
               <p>Upon this conſideration it is, that our Loyal Divines ſhould have a ſpecial regard, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther openly, or covertly, they increaſe their Auditories ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or diſtruſt of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties kindneſs to our Church, but rather inforce a free paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of the contrary to our very heart and ſouls; ſo as firſt to be truly thankful for his grace, and then to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:99791:113"/>of it: They have li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty from the King to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm their Auditors with the beſt Reaſons they can (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out miſrepreſentations) in their Religion. But withal, I think it likewiſe neceſſary, they be taught not to harbour thoſe doubts, and apprehenſions of any Intendment of the King by any power to inforce us to abandon it, but rather in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage them in a firm and thankful belief, that the King will make good his gracious Promiſe. Some ſuch Cordials would preſerve our Religion, better than all the bewailings of the afflicted State of the Church, which will not ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure us one Article of our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
               <p>I can foreſee no danger to the Church of <hi>England</hi> by
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:99791:113"/>this way of proceeding, but am moſt aſſured it would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline his Majeſty more chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to continue his protection of it, in finding ſuch grateful returns of his Favours.</p>
               <p>Only it might produce one effect, that ſome probably are not deſireous to experience, that it would again bring us to that Criterion, and perfect di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of thoſe who are true Members of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> from others that now wear the Badge and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very only, which they can as ſoon undreſs themſelves of, when they ſhould judge it for their Intereſt. We ſhould then find them at their old Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, that the Clergy were going over to, or meeting half-way the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> and even thoſe who are ſo much
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:99791:114"/>applauded and followed, would in a little time be accuſed of ſelling the Reverſion of our Religion, as in the late times they were ſcandalized with the Incumbering and Mort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging of it.</p>
               <p>Upon the whole let us ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly conſider, that where Loyalty obtains, no people can be miſerable, let us truſt God and the King. And tho there are differences in point of Doctrine, betwixt the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholics and us: Yet as we agree in Morals, and in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral indiſputable Points of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanity, in the Creeds, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Articles of Faith, as well as in ſome external Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies (rejected by other Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants) there is no reaſon we ſhould keep up ſuch inveterate Animoſities, be at perpetual
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:99791:114"/>ſtrife, not <hi>de finibus regundis;</hi> but of exterminating one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. But rather ſtudy how by an amicable accord in our common Duty of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Allegiance we may mutually and Cordially endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the defence and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the King and his Government, which ought to be every Loyal mans deſign, and is the ſole intendment of this my preſent writing to you.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
